. >> GOOD AFTERNOON WELCOME TO
THE SEPTEMBER 2ND 2025 REGULAR MEETING OF THE SAN FRANCISCO
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. >> MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL? THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
>> SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN PRESENTS
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY PRESENT SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO
AND ENGARDIO PRESENT SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER PRESENT
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD PRESENT SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN
PRESENT MANDEL MEN PRESENT SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR
PRESENT SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER PRESENT SUPERVISOR
CHERYL CHERYL PRESENT AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON
PRESENT MR. PRESIDENT ALL MEMBERS ARE PRESENT.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL
HOMELAND OF THE RAMAKRISHNA ALONI WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL
INHABITANTS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PENINSULA AS THE
INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF THIS LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE WITH
THEIR TRADITIONS THEIR ARMY TO SALONI HAVE NEVER CEDED LOSS
NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE
CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO
RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL TERRITORY AS GUESTS WE
RECOGNIZE THAT WE BENEFIT FROM LIVING AND WORKING ON THEIR
TRADITIONAL HOMELANDS. WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY
ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE
ROMITA ALONI COMMUNITY AND BY AFFIRMING THEIR SOVEREIGN
RIGHTS AS FIRST PEOPLES. COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME
IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF ALLEGIANCE?
ALLEGIANCE TO THE FLAG OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA AND TO
THE REPUBLIC IS ONE NATION UNDER GOD INDIVISIBLE WITH
LIBERTY. >> ON BEHALF OF OUR BOARD I
WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF AT US OF GOV TV TODAY
PARTICULARLY KALEENA MENDOZA. THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR
MEETINGS AND MAKE THE TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE TO THE
PUBLIC ONLINE. >> MADAM CLERK, DO YOU HAVE ANY
COMMUNICATIONS? YES.
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS WELCOMES YOU ALL TO ATTEND THIS MEETING IN PERSON
HERE IN THE LEGISLATIVE CHAMBER WHICH IS LOCATED WITHIN CITY
HALL IN ROOM 250 OR YOU MAY WATCH THE PROCEEDING ON S.F.
GOV'T TV'S CHANNEL 26 OR VIEW THE LIVESTREAM AT W W W DOT
S.F. OR VTV.ORG. IF YOU WOULD LIKE TO SUBMIT
YOUR PUBLIC COMMENT IN WRITING YOU CAN SEND IT VIA EMAIL TO B
O S AT S.F. CODE.ORG OR USE THE POSTAL SERVICE JUST ADDRESS THE
ENVELOPE TO THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
THE NUMBER ONE DR. CARLETON CAPITAL B GOOD PLACE CITY HALL
ROOM 244 SAN FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA 94102 IF YOU NEED TO
MAKE A FUTURE REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION AND REQUEST UNDER
THE AMERICANS WITH DISABILITIES ACT OR IF YOU NEED LANGUAGE
ASSISTANCE PLEASE CONTACT THE CLERK'S OFFICE AT LEAST TWO
BUSINESS DAYS IN ADVANCE. OUR PHONE NUMBER IS
(415) 554-5184. THANK YOU MR. PRESIDENT.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. LET'S GO TO APPROVAL OF OUR
MEETING MINUTES. APPROVAL OF THE JULY 1ST JULY
EIGHTH, JULY 15TH AND JULY 22ND 2025 BOARD MEETING MINUTES.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. MAY I HAVE A MOTION TO APPROVE
THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED MOVED BY MELGAR SECONDED BY WALTON.
MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MINUTES AS
PRESENTED? SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I'S
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN ALL RIGHT
MANDEL MEN EYES SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR
SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I'M SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON
EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I AND SUPERVISOR ENGARDIO
AND ENGARDIO EITHER ARE LEBANESE.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MINUTES WILL BE APPROVED AFTER
PUBLIC COMMENT AS PRESENTED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO THE
CONSENT AGENDA ITEMS ONE THROUGH FOUR ITEMS ONE THROUGH
FOUR ARE ON CONSENT. THESE ITEMS ARE CONSIDERED TO
BE ROUTINE AND IF A MEMBER OBJECTS AN ITEM MAY BE REMOVED
AND CONSIDERED SEPARATELY. >> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON
ITEMS ONE THROUGH FOUR. SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I.E.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I
RANDLEMAN I'M SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I'M SUPERVISOR SADR SADR
EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I AND SUPERVISOR ENGARDIO
AND ENGARDIO EITHER ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THESE
ORDINANCES ARE FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO
UNFINISHED BUSINESS PLEASE CALL ITEM FIVE ITEM FIVE THIS IS AN
ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO PROMOTE
EQUITABLE ACCESS TO SHELTER AND BEHAVIORAL HEALTH SERVICES
BY PROHIBITING THE CITY FROM SITING A NEW CITY FUNDED
HOMELESS SHELTER TRANSITIONAL HOUSING FACILITY OR CERTAIN
BEHAVIORAL HEALTH RESIDENTIAL CARE AND TREATMENT FACILITIES
COLLECTIVELY KNOWN AS COVERED FACILITIES IN A NEIGHBORHOOD
WHERE THE NEIGHBORHOOD SHARE OF THE CITY'S SHELTER
AND TRANSITIONAL HOUSING BEDS EXCEEDS THE NEIGHBORHOOD SHARE
OF THE CITY'S UNSHELTERED PERSONS AND TO PROHIBIT THE
CITY FROM SITING A NEW CITY FUNDED HOMELESS SHELTER WITHIN
300FT OF AN EXISTING HOMELESS SHELTER AND TO AUTHORIZE THE
BOARD TO WAIVE THESE PROHIBITIONS UPON FINDING THAT
APPROVING THE COVERED FACILITY OR HOMELESS SHELTER AT THE
PROPOSED LOCATION IS IN THE PUBLIC INTEREST AND TO PROVIDE
A SUNSET DATE OF DECEMBER 31ST 2031 PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON
ITEM FIVE SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD
MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MANDELL MAN I SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER I SUPERVISOR
CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHAN
CHAN NO SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN NO SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
AND SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO AND ENGARDIO I THERE ARE NINE
EYES AND TWO NOSE WITH SUPERVISORS CHAN AND CHEN
VOTING NO THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK
PLEASE CALL ITEM SIX ITEM SIX THIS IS AN ORDINANCE THAT WAS
REFERRED WITHOUT RECOMMENDATION FROM THE LAND USE
AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE. IT AMENDS THE PLANNING CODE TO
ELIMINATE LIMITS ON NONRESIDENTIAL USE SIZES IN THE
FOLLOWING NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL DISTRICTS THE
PACIFIC AVENUE POLK STREET WEST PORTAL AVENUE, NORTH BEACH, THE
NORTH BEACH SPECIAL USE DISTRICT REGIONAL COMMERCIAL
DISTRICTS AND RESIDENTIAL COMMERCIAL DISTRICTS AND TO
ALLOW SPECIFIED NON RESIDENTIAL USES THAT EXCEED THE USE SIZE
LIMITS TO DIVIDE INTO SMALLER SPACES THAT MAY CONTINUE TO
EXCEED THE USE SIZE LIMITS WITHOUT CONDITIONAL USE
AUTHORIZATION TO FURTHER ADJUST THE USE SIZE LIMIT IN ALL NCDS
TO AROUND NUMBER AND TO AFFIRM THE SECOND DETERMINATION AND TO
MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS PLEASE CALL THE ROLL IN THIS
ITEM ON ITEM SIX SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN HI MANDELL AND I
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SAUDER SAUDER I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN NO SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN NO
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I AND SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO
AND GUARDIAN I THERE ARE NINE EYES AND TWO NOS WITH
SUPERVISORS CHEN AND CHEN VOTING NO THE ORDINANCE IS
FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM SEVEN ITEM
SEVEN THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE
TO REVISE THE GOALS AND REPORTING REQUIREMENTS FOR
FOOD PURCHASING BY THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH
AND SHERIFF'S DEPARTMENT FOR CITY HOSPITALS AND JAILS AND TO
ELIMINATE THE SUNSET DATE SUCH THAT THE PROGRAMS, STANDARDS
AND REPORTING REQUIREMENTS WILL REMAIN IN EFFECT INDEFINITELY.
>> SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU PRESIDENT, MADAM
AND COLLEAGUES. BEFORE AUGUST RECESS WE AMENDED
THIS FILE TO ADD AN EXPIRATION DATE AND REMOVE THE PERCENTAGE
GOALS FOR THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH TO ALLOW THEM
MORE TIME FOR DISCUSSION. BEFORE RECESS WE AMENDED THE
FILE TO ADD AN EXPIRATION DATE AND REMOVED THE PERCENTAGE
GOALS FOR DISPATCH. >> NOW THEY HAVE REACHED AN
AGREEMENT ON THEIR GOALS AND I WOULD LIKE TO MAKE A MOTION TO
AMEND THIS LEGISLATION TO REFLECT THAT BEFORE THIS POLICY
EXPIRES LATER THIS MONTH AND THE AMENDMENTS READ AS ON
PAGE SIX LINES 20 THROUGH 22 AT THE FOLLOWING LANGUAGE SHALL
SOURCE 5% OF FOOD FROM MEDIUM TO SMALL FARMS BY JANUARY 2027
AND INCREASE SOURCING FROM MEDIUM SMALL FARMS TO 5 TO 7%
BY JANUARY 20TH 28 AND TO 10 TO 15% BY JANUARY 2032.
ON PAGE SEVEN LINES 23 TO 24 SECTION 21 D3 AT THE FOLLOWING
CLARIFICATION FOR PATIENT DIETARY PROTOCOLS WE WILL
CONTINUE TO ADHERE TO PATIENT DIETARY PROTOCOL LAWS IF PLANT
BASED FOODS ARE NOT APPROPRIATE SUBSTITUTES FOR A PATIENT
AND THESE AMENDMENTS HAVE BEEN SUBMITTED TO EVERYONE AS WELL.
>> AND SO I'D LIKE TO MAKE A MOTION TO AMEND ITEM NUMBER
SEVEN WITH THESE AMENDMENTS. SO THERE'S BEEN A MOTION MADE
BY SUPERVISOR WALTON SECONDED BY SUPERVISOR CHAN.
COLLEAGUES, CAN WE TAKE THE AMENDMENT WITHOUT OBJECTION?
I THINK WE CAN WITHOUT WITHOUT OBJECTION.
>> THE AMENDMENT IS APPROVED AND MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU CALL
THE ROLL ON THE ORDINANCE AS AMENDED ON ITEM SEVEN AS
AMENDED SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I'S SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD
MAHMOOD EYES SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN.
ALL RIGHT, GENTLEMEN, I'M SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I'M SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I'M
SUPERVISOR WALTON I WALTON I'M SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
AND SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO AND ENGARDIO EITHER ARE
LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST
READING AS AMENDED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO NEW BUSINESS PLEASE
CALL ITEMS EIGHT AND NINE TOGETHER ITEMS EIGHT AND NINE
ARE TWO RESOLUTIONS THAT DETERMINE IF THE PERSON TO
PERSON PREMISE TO PREMISE TRANSFER AND AN ISSUANCE OF A
LIQUOR LICENSE WILL SERVE THE PUBLIC CONVENIENCE FOR ITEM
EIGHT THIS IS A TYPE 21 OFF SALE GENERAL BEER, WINE
AND DISTILLED SPIRITS LIQUOR LICENSE TO JUMBO TRADING
COMPANY LLC LOCATED AT 761 JACKSON STREET AND FOR ITEM
NINE THIS IS A TYPE 90 ISSUANCE ON SALE GENERAL MUSIC VENUE
LIQUOR LICENSE TO UNIVERSAL LIFE CAROL LLC DOING BUSINESS
AS THE STUD LOCATED AT 1123 FOLSOM STREET AND TO REQUEST
THAT THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF ALCOHOLIC BEVERAGE CONTROL
IMPOSE CONDITIONS ON THE ISSUANCE OF EACH LICENSE.
>> ALL RIGHT, COLLEAGUES, I THINK WE CAN TAKE THESE ITEMS
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE
ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK, WE DON'T HAVE
COMMITTEE REPORTS TODAY SO LET'S GO TO ROLL CALL FIRST
MEMBER TO INTRODUCE NEW BUSINESSES SUPERVISOR FIELDER
SUBMIT THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD GOOD
AFTERNOON COLLEAGUES. >> IT'S GOOD TO BE BACK
AND GOOD TO SEE EVERYONE AS WELL.
>> I WANT TO SHARE A STORY THAT I HAVEN'T TOLD BEFORE.
I SHARED IT EARLIER IN THE STEPS OF CITY HALL AS I
INTRODUCE A RESOLUTION IN SUPPORT OF PROPOSITION 15
WHICH IS THAT YEARS AGO I LIVED UNDER A DICTATORSHIP AS A
TEENAGER I LIVED IN PAKISTAN AFTER AUTHORITARIAN LEADER WHO
TOOK THE COUNTRY FROM A DEMOCRACY TO A DICTATORSHIP
UNDER THE GUISE OF SAFETY AND SECURITY.
>> SLOWLY I SAW HOW THAT DICTATOR STRIPPED AWAY THE
INSTITUTIONS THAT WE THOUGHT WE COULD RELY ON FOR CHANGE FROM
THE JUDICIARY TO THE CONSTITUTION.
>> I SAW TERROR BEING USED AS AN EXCUSE TO QUICKLY SEIZE MORE
POWER AND TAKE AWAY FUNDAMENTAL HUMAN RIGHTS AMERICAN
DEMOCRACY. >> I KNEW THOUGH WAS DIFFERENT.
>> IT'S WHAT GAVE MY FAMILY THE OPPORTUNITY TO TRULY BREAK INTO
THE MIDDLE CLASS. ONCE WE RETURNED TO THE STATES
AND GAVE ME THE CHANCE TO PROUDLY SERVE OUR CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO AND IT'S THE REASON THAT WE
CONTINUE TO BE ABLE TO GATHER HERE TODAY AND SPEAK FREELY
WHETHER ON THE STEPS OF CITY HALL OR IN THE CHAMBERS THAT WE
ARE SITTING IN. >> BUT THESE FREEDOMS
IN AMERICA WE HAVE TO RECOGNIZE ARE STILL NOT A GIVEN.
>> WE CAN SEE MORE CLEARLY NOW THAN EVER THE CRACKS IN OUR
FRAGILE DEMOCRACY. OUR DEMOCRACY IS UNDER ATTACK
AND THE OPPOSITION ISN'T EVEN TRYING TO HIDE IT.
WHAT WE'RE SEEING FROM THE WHITE HOUSE AND TRUMP'S ALLIES
FOR REDISTRICTING IN TEXAS IS AN OVERT EFFORT TO RIG OUR
ELECTIONS. >> IT'S A GROWING AND CLEAR
MESSAGE THAT THIS ADMINISTRATION WILL DO ANYTHING
TO SEIZE MORE POWER. >> IT'S A TERRIFYING PATTERN
THAT I'VE SEEN PERSONALLY BEFORE LIVING IN THE STREETS OF
LAHORE AND WE CAN'T SIT IDLY BY WITH OUR HANDS TIED BEHIND OUR
BACKS WAITING FOR A CHECK AND BALANCE TO REIN IN THESE
POWER GRABS. >> THERE'S SIMPLY TOO MUCH AT
STAKE. >> THE 2020 SIX ELECTION IS
JUST AROUND THE CORNER AND THIS ADMINISTRATION AND IN THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT HAS SHOWN IT WILL STOP AT NOTHING TO
CONTINUE PUSHING ITS HATE FILLED AGENDA THAT HURTS OUR
IMMIGRANTS, HURTS OUR WORKING FAMILIES, HURTS OUR SENIORS.
>> WE'VE SEEN WHAT THEY'VE ALREADY DONE WITH THEIR BIG
UGLY BILL TO TARGET MEDICARE AND MEDICAID, ROLL BLACK BACK
CLEAN ENERGY INVESTMENTS AND LAUNCH TARGETED ICE RAIDS
PUTTING OUR MOST MARGINALIZED COMMUNITIES AT RISK.
>> BUT WE CAN ALWAYS AND SHOULD ALWAYS FIGHT BACK.
>> THAT'S WHY TODAY I'M INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION
IN SUPPORT OF GOVERNOR NEWSOM'S PROP 52 PUSH BACK AGAINST MAGA
ELECTION RIGGING PLANS OFTENTIMES BECAUSE THE BEST
DEFENSE IS A GOOD OFFENSE AND IN SUPPORTING PROPOSITION
50 WE'RE SENDING A CLEAR MESSAGE BACK TO OUR FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT IN THIS CITY WE DON'T TOLERATE AUTHORITARIANS.
WE STAND UNITED WITH OUR WORKING FAMILIES, WITH OUR
SENIORS, WITH OUR IMMIGRANT COMMUNITIES AND HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO WE STAND TOGETHER FOR OUR DEMOCRACY, FOR OUR FREEDOM
AND FOR OUR COUNTRY. THANK YOU TO SUPERVISORS DORSEY
CHERYL CHEN SAUDER, WALTON CHAN AND PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN FOR
YOUR EARLY SUPPORT AND I HOPE COLLEAGUES HAVE YOUR SUPPORT AS
WELL. >> THANK YOU.
SECOND, I WANTED TO PROVIDE AN UPDATE ON SOME OF THE OUTSIDE
BOARDS AND COMMISSIONS I SERVE ON.
I HAVE THE PLEASURE OF SERVING ALONGSIDE SUPERVISOR WALTON
AND ENVIRONMENT DIRECTOR TYRONE JOO ON THE BAY AREA DISTRICT
BOARD. RECENTLY WE APPROVED THE AIR
DISTRICT'S $312 MILLION BUDGET EARLIER THIS SUMMER WHICH
INCLUDED NEW ENVIRONMENTAL JUSTICE AND OUTREACH ROLES
SUPPORTING PROGRAMS THAT SERVE COMMUNITIES AFFECTED BY AIR
POLLUTION. THE BUDGET REFLECTS AN INCREASE
IN FINES TO REFINERIES AND OTHER LARGE POLLUTERS AN
INCREASED FEES TO ENSURE THAT ENFORCEMENT PROGRAMS COVER MORE
OF THEIR COSTS. >> THE AIR DISTRICT WAS ACTIVE
IN SACRAMENTO AS WELL AS SUPPORTING BILLS THAT INCREASE
THE SCOPE OF THE CLEAN CARS FOR ALL PROGRAM AND CREATE FUNDING
OPPORTUNITIES FOR AIR QUALITY MONITORING.
>> A FUN ANECDOTE THAT I'LL SHARE WITH MY COLLEAGUES IS
THAT THE PRIMARY OPPOSITION I BELIEVE TO CLEAN CARS FOR ALL
WAS JAY LENO THAT COMEDIAN DUDE .
>> BUT OUR ENEMIES IN CALIFORNIA I ALSO HAD THE
HONOR OF REPRESENTING THE AIR DISTRICT AS A SPEAKER AT ALL
ABOARD BAY AREA TRANSIT DAY ADVOCATING FOR PUBLIC
TRANSPORTATION AND ITS CRITICAL ROLE IN PROTECTING AIR QUALITY
IN THE BAY AREA. I LOOK FORWARD TO CONTINUING TO
REPRESENT SAN FRANCISCO IN SUPPORTING THE AIR DISTRICT
ALONGSIDE SUPERVISOR WALTON IN COMBATING AIR POLLUTION
AND CREATING A SAFER, HEALTHIER REGION.
>> THE REST I SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD. SUPERVISOR MENDELSOHN.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM
INTRODUCING A RENEWAL OF THE PAYMENT WAIVER RESOLUTION THAT
WE APPROVED BACK IN FEBRUARY FOR THE OFFICES OF THE MAYOR,
CITY ATTORNEY ASSESSOR RECORDER AND CITY ADMINISTRATOR TO
SOLICIT DONATIONS TO COVER GOODS AND SERVICES INCLUDING
LEGAL SERVICES TO PROTECT OUR IMMIGRANT AND LGBT Q PLUS
COMMUNITIES AND DEFEND REPRODUCTIVE RIGHTS,
ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTIONS AND RACIAL EQUITY EFFORTS.
I'M ALSO INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION DESIGNATING
SEPTEMBER 2025 AS CHILDHOOD CANCER AWARENESS MONTH IN THE
CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
EVERY YEAR MORE THAN 16,000 AMERICAN CHILDREN ARE DIAGNOSED
WITH CANCER. GLOBALLY AN ESTIMATED 400,000
CHILDREN AND ADOLESCENTS ARE DIAGNOSED EACH YEAR.
CHILDHOOD CANCER REMAINS THE LEADING CAUSE OF DEATH BY
DISEASE FOR US CHILDREN BETWEEN INFANCY AND AGE 15.
HERE IN THE BAY AREA AND ESPECIALLY RIGHT HERE
IN SAN FRANCISCO, WE'RE FORTUNATE TO HAVE SOME OF THE
LEADING INSTITUTIONS WORKING ON THE FRONT LINES OF TREATMENT
RESEARCH AND FAMILY SUPPORT INCLUDING UCSF BENIOFF
CHILDREN'S HOSPITAL, SUTTER HEALTH CALIFORNIA AND LUCILE
PACKARD CHILDREN'S HOSPITAL AT STANFORD.
YET OUR PROGRESS IN TACKLING CHILDHOOD CANCERS THREATENED BY
THE CURRENT EROSION OF FEDERAL RESEARCH SUPPORT IN THE YEAR
END 2024 SPENDING PACKAGE, CONGRESS REMOVED KEY PROVISIONS
THAT WOULD HAVE SUPPORTED PEDIATRIC CANCER RESEARCH SUCH
AS THE ACCELERATING KIDS TO RESEARCH ACT, THE CREATING HOPE
REAUTHORIZATION ACT AND THE GIVE KIDS THE CHANCE ACT.
THESE PROGRAMS WERE MEANT TO IMPROVE ACCESS TO MEDICINE,
INCENTIVIZE DRUG DEVELOPMENT AND SUPPORT INNOVATIVE
COMBINATION THERAPIES. FEDERAL FUNDING FOR PEDIATRIC
CANCER RESEARCH HAS LONG BEEN INSUFFICIENT.
ONLY ABOUT 4% OF THE NATIONAL CANCER INSTITUTE'S CANCER
RESEARCH BUDGET GOES TOWARD PEDIATRIC CANCERS.
COUPLED WITH RECENT FUNDING INSTABILITY INCLUDING PROPOSED
NIH BUDGET CUTS, VITAL CLINICAL TRIALS, STAFFING AND THE
OVERARCHING SCIENTIFIC INFRASTRUCTURE ARE ALL AT RISK.
THAT'S WHY COMMUNITY BASED SUPPORT IS MORE CRITICAL THAN
EVER. FOR MORE THAN 30 YEARS,
ORGANIZATIONS LIKE THE AMERICAN CANCER FUND FOR CHILDREN, KIDS
CANCER CONNECTION AND LIONS CLUBS INTERNATIONAL HAVE
STEPPED UP PROVIDING PSYCHOSOCIAL SERVICES FOR
CHILDREN UNDERGOING TREATMENT. >> I WANT TO THANK DR. AMY
AND STEVEN FIRESTEIN FOR ALERTING MY OFFICE TO CHILDHOOD
CANCER AWARENESS MONTH AND WORKING WITH MELANIE
MATHISON IN MY OFFICE ON THIS RESOLUTION.
AND I WANT TO THANK CO-SPONSORS SUPERVISORS SHERYL AND GARCIA
CHEN MELGAR, SAUTTER AND FIELDER.
I HAVE A BRIEF UPDATE FROM THE TRANSBAY JOINT POWERS AUTHORITY
BOARD WHERE I SERVE AS VICE CHAIR.
LAST WEEK THE TPA RECEIVED NOTICE THAT THE FEDERAL
RAILROAD ADMINISTRATION HAS DECIDED TO WITHDRAW OUR AWARDED
$24.5 MILLION GRANT FOR THE DOWNTOWN RAIL EXTENSIONS
DESIGNED FOR TRACK AND RAIL SYSTEMS.
IN A SUBSEQUENT PRESS RELEASE, TRANSPORTATION SECRETARY DUFFY
ALSO WITHDREW FUNDING FOR A NUMBER OF OTHER PROJECTS
RELATED TO CALIFORNIA HIGH SPEED RAIL.
ALTHOUGH DISAPPOINTING THIS LOSS OF FUNDING IS NOT FATAL
FOR EITHER THE DOWNTOWN RAIL EXTENSION OR THE PORTAL AND THE
PROJECTS WILL CONTINUE TO MOVE FORWARD WITH OTHER LOCAL,
REGIONAL AND STATE FUNDS. FINALLY I'M ASKING THAT WE
ADJOURN TODAY'S MEETING IN MEMORY OF FATHER MARIO PAUL
FARINA WHO DIED ON AUGUST FIFTH, 2025 AT THE AGE OF 80.
>> MARIO FIORANO WAS BORN IN SAN FRANCISCO IN 1944,
ATTENDED EPIPHANY GRAMMAR SCHOOL AND GRADUATED FROM THE
UNIVERSITY OF SANTA CLARA BEFORE ENTERING ST PATRICK'S
SEMINARY IN THE LATE 1960S. AFTER HIS RETIREMENT, FATHER
FARINA SERVED AS ASSOCIATE PASTOR AND AS PASTOR TO A
NUMBER OF PARISHES IN SAN FRANCISCO ST KEVIN ST JOHN ST
CATHERINE'S ST MICHAEL'S ST STEPHEN ST PAUL'S ST PHILIP THE
APOSTLE AND ST JAMES. HE ALSO ACTED FIRST TIME AS
CHAIRMAN OF THE MISSION DEANERY COUNCIL CHAPLAIN AT SACRED
HEART HIGH AND VOCATIONS DIRECTOR OF THE SAN FRANCISCO
DIOCESE WHERE HE ENCOURAGED, ADVISED AND MENTORED
INDIVIDUALS SEEKING THE PRIESTHOOD.
IN 1993, AFTER PREVIOUSLY SERVING AS ITS ASSOCIATE PASTOR
FATHER FOR ON A RETURN TO ST PAUL'S CATHOLIC CHURCH IN NOVI
VALLEY AS ITS PASTOR A POST HE WOULD HOLD UNTIL HIS DEATH BACK
IN 1993. HOWEVER, IT WAS NOT CLEAR THE
ASSIGNMENT WOULD BE A LONG ONE. IN THE AUTUMN AND AUTUMN OF
THAT YEAR ST PAUL'S WAS ON A LIST OF CHURCHES TO BE CLOSED
FOREVER AS PART OF A DIOCESE REORGANIZATION PLAN LED BY
THEIR NEW PASTOR. THE PARISHIONERS OF SAINT
PAUL'S PROTESTED THE CLOSURE AND SUCCESSFULLY PERSUADED
OFFICIALS TO PRESERVE THE CHURCH.
IT WAS THE ONLY CHURCH ON THE DIOCESE'S CLOSURE LIST TO
REMAIN OPEN. OVER THE SUBSEQUENT 30 YEARS,
FATHER FARINA WOULD BECOME A TRULY BELOVED FIGURE IN THE ST
PAUL'S AND BROADER NOVI VALLEY COMMUNITY.
I FEEL FORTUNATE TO HAVE HAD THE OPPORTUNITY TO MEET HIM
IN OCTOBER OF LAST YEAR WHEN I PRESENTED HIM WITH A
CERTIFICATE OF HONOR FOR HIS LIFETIME OF SERVICE
AND ESPECIALLY HIS DEDICATION TO ST PAUL'S.
HE RAISED MILLIONS OF DOLLARS FOR PROJECTS TO ENSURE THAT THE
CHURCH WOULD LAST WELL BEYOND HIS PASTOR SHIP.
THE PROJECTS COMPLETED ON ON HIS WATCH INCLUDE A SEISMIC
RETROFIT OF THE CHURCH, THE REPLACEMENT OF THE SLATE ROOF,
THE REFURBISHMENT OF THE STEEPLE CROSSES WITH GOLD LEAF
THE BUILDING OF A NEW SCHOOL AND A RESTORATION OF ALL THE
CHURCHES GERMAN MADE LATE 19TH CENTURY STAINED GLASS WINDOWS.
FATHER MARIO FARINA WAS THE CONSUMMATE STEWARD OF A PLACE
THAT AS HE DESCRIBED IT WAS WHERE CELEBRATIONS IN PEOPLE'S
LIVES HAVE TAKEN PLACE BOTH HAPPY ONES AND SORROWFUL ONES.
WEDDINGS AND BAPTISMS AND CONFIRMATIONS IT'S A PLACE
WHERE PEOPLE CAN GATHER AND GET SUPPORT TO HAVE THAT SENSE OF
FAMILY AND COMMUNITY TO FEEL AND UNDERSTAND THAT THEY ARE
NOT ISOLATED NOR ALONE. REST IN PEACE FATHER MARIO
FARINA. MAY YOUR MEMORY BE A BLESSING
AND THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISE, SIR MELGAR. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES, I HOPE EVERYONE HAD A GOOD REST IN AUGUST.
I'M GLAD TO SEE EVERYONE BACK. TODAY I AM INTRODUCING A FEW
THINGS. FIRST I PROPOSE TO INTRODUCE A
RESOLUTION PROCLAIMING SEPTEMBER 2025 AS THE 10TH
ANNUAL SAN FRANCISCO TRANSIT MONTH.
PUBLIC TRANSIT IS NOT JUST HOW WE MOVE AROUND.
IT IS THE BACKBONE OF OUR CITY'S LIVABILITY, SAFETY,
ECONOMY AND VITALITY ALSO OUR CLIMATE FUTURE.
MUNI ALONE CARRIES MORE RIDERS THAN ALL OF THEIR BAY AREA
AGENCIES COMBINED. AND IT IS ESSENTIAL FOR
SENIORS, YOUNG PEOPLE, PEOPLE WITH DISABILITY WORKING
FAMILIES ANYONE WHO DEPENDS ON AN AFFORDABLE, RELIABLE WAY TO
GET AROUND. AND AS WE ALL KNOW WE'RE AT A
CROSSROADS. MUNI BART CALTRAIN ARE ALL
FACING FISCAL CLIFFS. IT'S THREATENING DEVASTATING
CUTS TO OUR SERVICES AND A THRIVING SAN FRANCISCO JUST
CANNOT EXIST WITHOUT A THRIVING TRANSPORTATION SYSTEM.
IF WE FAIL TO ACT WE JEOPARDIZE OUR CLIMATE GOALS OUR DOWNTOWN
RECOVERY, THE ABILITY OF OUR RESIDENTS TO GET TO WORK SCHOOL
PLAY TRANSIT MONTH IS A CHANCE TO CELEBRATE RIDERS BUT ALSO TO
HIGHLIGHT OUR OPERATORS TO ENCOURAGE MORE SAN FRANCISCANS
TO RIDE AROUND AND TO RECOMMIT OURSELVES TO FIGHTING FOR
SUSTAINABLE FUNDING SO THAT TRANSIT REMAINS FREQUENT,
AFFORDABLE, DEPENDABLE AND SAFE.
SO LET US MARK THIS TEN YEAR OF TRANSIT MONTH NOT ONLY WITH A
CELEBRATION BUT WITH URGENCY BECAUSE A FEATURE OF SAN
FRANCISCO DEPENDS ON STRONG, WELL-FUNDED PUBLIC TRANSIT.
I WANT TO REMIND US THAT IT IS ALSO A CONTEST.
>> THERE IS A LEADER BOARD FOR ELECTED OFFICIALS OURSELVES.
AND YOU COULD LOG EVERY RIDE THAT YOU TAKE ON ANY PUBLIC
TRANSPORTATION SYSTEM IN THE BAY AREA AND IT'S KIND OF FUN.
>> I'M ALSO INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION SUPPORTING SCHOOL
ATTENDANCE IN THE BE THEIR CAMPAIGN BE HERE CAMPAIGN.
COLLEAGUES I AM INTRODUCING THIS RESOLUTION ALONG WITH THE
SAN FRANCISCO UNIFIED SCHOOL DISTRICT IN THEIR CAMPAIGN TO
COMBAT CHRONIC ABSENTEEISM AND TO BUILD A CULTURE OF
BELONGING AMONG OUR PUBLIC SCHOOL STUDENTS.
CHRONIC ABSENTEEISM MEANS MISSING MORE THAN 10% OF YOUR
SCHOOL YEAR JUST TWO DAYS A MONTH.
IT MAY NOT SOUND LIKE MUCH BUT CONSEQUENCES ARE ACTUALLY QUITE
SEVERE. HIGHER RISK OF ACADEMIC FAILURE
DROPPING OUT LASTING HARM TO STUDENT WELL-BEING THAT CARRIES
ACTUALLY THROUGH TO ADULTHOOD. I HIGH ABSENTEEISM IN THE FIRST
FEW YEARS OF SCHOOL HAS EVEN BEEN SHOWN TO LEAD TO HIGHER
INVOLVEMENT IN THE JUVENILE JUSTICE SYSTEM WHERE SFO IS D
HAS MADE PROGRESS SINCE THE PANDEMIC REDUCING ABSENTEEISM
FROM 29% TO 22% TO 23% IN 2024. IT IS STILL FAR ABOVE
PRE-PANDEMIC LEVELS AT 14% AND THE IMPACTS ARE NOT EQUAL.
FOSTER YOUTH HOMELESS YOUTH AFRICAN AMERICAN AND PACIFIC
ISLANDER STUDENTS FACE RATES ABOVE 40 AND 50%.
THE SCALE MATTERS. IN 2024 STUDENTS MISSED OVER
670,000 DAYS OF SCHOOL COSTING NEARLY 55 MILLION IN LOST STATE
FUNDING BUT ALSO HAVING A DEFICIT EFFECT ON THEIR LIVES.
WE MUST SUPPORT THESE STUDENTS AND THEIR FAMILIES WITH A TWO
GENERATION STRATEGY. IF WE CAN CUT ABSENTEEISM
IN HALF, NOT ONLY DO OUTCOMES IMPROVE FOR CHILDREN BUT AS A
PRIORITY COULD NEARLY CLOSE THE BUDGET DEFICIT WITHOUT ANY
ADDITIONAL CUTS. THE BE HERE CAMPAIGN IS A
COLLABORATIVE MULTIYEAR EFFORT TO SUPPORT FAMILIES, ADDRESS
BARRIERS TO ATTENDANCE, STRENGTHEN STUDENT SUCCESS.
SEPTEMBER IS ATTENDANCE AWARENESS MONTH AND THIS IS A
MOMENT TO REAFFIRM THAT SAN FRANCISCO BELIEVES EVERY CHILD
DESERVES TO BE HERE AND THRIVE .
LASTLY, I AM INTRODUCING A PROCLAMATION ON NAMING
SEPTEMBER 14TH HATCH DAY FOR CLAUDE THE ALBINO ALLIGATOR.
CLAUDE IS TURNING THE BIG THREE ZERO AND WE ARE CELEBRATING ALL
MONTH LONG. >> I WOULD LIKE TO INVITE YOU
ALL TO CLAUDE'S 30TH HATCH DAY PARTY ON SUNDAY SEPTEMBER 14TH
FROM 11 TO 1230 AT THE ACADEMY. WE ARE GOING TO HAVE A BIRTHDAY
SING ALONG. >> A FISH CAKE FOR CLAUDE
CUPCAKES FOR GUESTS AND PHOTOS WITH THE GUEST OF HONOR.
>> WE ALL CAN USE A LITTLE GOOD NEWS THESE DAYS AND IN THE
CURRENT NATIONAL CLIMATE, SUPPORT FOR SCIENCE
INSTITUTIONS IS MORE IMPORTANT THAN EVER.
SO I AM INTRODUCING THIS AS A PROCLAMATION AND HOPE TO HAVE
YOUR SUPPORT. LASTLY, I WILL UPDATE YOU ON MY
OUTSIDE COMMISSION INVOLVEMENT WHICH IS THE MTC AND AS PART OF
THE NTC AT THE BAY AREA HOUSING FINANCE AGENCY.
>> AND I WANTED TO REPORT THAT THE BOARD OF THE MTC DID
APPROVE THE RESOLUTION SUPPORTING SB 63 THE REGIONAL
TAX MEASURE TO SUPPORT PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION.
>> IT WILL INCLUDE FUNDING OPERATIONAL FUNDING FOR MTA,
BART CALTRAIN FERRIES AND ALL THE OTHER SMALLER OPERATORS
AROUND THE BAY AREA. >> IT WILL.
IT IS AS WE ALL KNOW, SORELY NEEDED.
ALSO I WANTED TO REPORT THAT THE BAY AREA HOUSING AGENCY
APPROVED A BUDGET AND A WORK PLAN THAT SUPPORTS SMALL SITE
ACQUISITION WHICH IS GOOD FOR SAN FRANCISCO WITH A SLIGHTLY
HIGHER RMI FOR FOLKS WHO PARTICIPATE TO 120% OF MY IT
INCLUDES WORKFORCE HOUSING AND THAT IS A WORK PLAN THAT
WAS APPROVED AS WELL. THANK YOU SO MUCH.
THANK YOU. >> SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
SUPERVISOR SAUDER AS COLLEAGUES TODAY I HAVE ONE RESOLUTION TO
INTRODUCE AND ONE IN MEMORIAM TO SHARE.
FIRST I'M PLEASED TO INTRODUCE A RESOLUTION COMMEMORATING THE
150TH ANNIVERSARY OF LAWRENCE FOUNTAIN.
YOU MAY KNOW A LOT AS FOUNTAIN AS THE 24 FOOT TALL CAST IRON
BRONZE ORNATE FOUNTAIN LOCATED AT THE INTERSECTION OF MARKET
KEARNY AND GEARY IN DISTRICT THREE BY A FEW FEET OR YOU MAY
KNOW A LOT AS FOUNTAIN AS A SPOT WHERE EVERY APRIL 18TH AT
5:12 A.M. FIREFIGHTERS, POLICE OFFICERS AND SOME BRAVE
RESIDENTS WHO SET THEIR ALARM CLOCKS PARTICIPATE IN A
MEMORIAL CEREMONY AT THE FOUNTAIN TO REMEMBER THE
VICTIMS OF THE 1906 EARTHQUAKE AND RECOGNIZE THE IMPORTANCE
THAT THE FOUNTAIN PLAYED IN THE AFTERMATH OF THAT TRAVEN
TRAGEDY. AS A CENTRAL MEETING POINT FOR
SAN FRANCISCANS SEEKING REFUGE FROM THE CITY'S RUINS.
WHAT YOU MIGHT NOT KNOW IS THAT LOT OF THE FOUNTAIN WAS ALSO
THE SITE OF A FAMOUS 1910 CHRISTMAS EVE PERFORMANCE BY
OPERA SINGER LUISA TETRAZZINI WHO DREW A CROWD OF 250,000
PEOPLE WHICH WAS REMARKABLE TO THE FOUNTAIN FOR THAT
PERFORMANCE. OR THAT A 2023 SURVEY CONDUCTED
BY THE SAN FRANCISCO MONUMENTS AND MEMORIAL'S ADVISORY
COMMITTEE FOUND LADIES FOUNTAIN TO BE THE MOST LIKED MONUMENT
OR MEMORIAL IN THE ENTIRE CIVIC ART COLLECTION.
BORN IN 1847, CHARLOTTE LATA CRABTREE WAS AN ACTRESS
ENTERTAINER, COMEDIAN AND PHILANTHROPIST AT ONE POINT
IN THE 1880S SHE WAS THE HIGHEST PAID ACTRESS IN THE
COUNTRY. SHE COMMISSIONED THIS FOUNTAIN
TO PROVIDE FREE DRINKING WATER TO THE PUBLIC AS AN EXPRESSION
OF HER GRATITUDE TO SAN FRANCISCO.
IT WAS GIFTED TO THE CITY AND COUNTY.
ON SEPTEMBER 9TH, 1875, 150 YEARS LATER IT STANDS AS A
TESTAMENT TO SAN FRANCISCO'S HISTORY, GENEROSITY OF ITS
PEOPLE AND BEAUTY OF CIVIC DESIGN.
I ALSO HAVE AN IN MEMORIAM TODAY FOR CHRISTINA TINA MOYLAN
WHO PASSED ON AUGUST 11TH. TINA WAS BORN IN SHERMAN OAKS,
CALIFORNIA ON FEBRUARY 17TH, 1948.
SHE MOVED NORTH TO SAN FRANCISCO TO ATTEND THE SAN
FRANCISCO COLLEGE FOR WOMEN WHERE SHE GRADUATED WITH A
BACHELORS IN BOTH FRENCH AND ART HISTORY.
SHE WOULD SOON MEET MIKE MOYLAN AND THEY WOULD WED THREE YEARS
LATER AND RAISE A SON KEVIN AND DAUGHTER KELLY IN THE
FAMILY. HIS JOB AND INTERESTS WOULD SEE
THEM MOVE OFTEN FROM SOME FROM SAN FRANCISCO TO SAN JOSE TO
ENGLAND TO SACRAMENTO AND BACK TO SAN FRANCISCO.
BUT NO MATTER WHERE SHE LIVED SHE ALWAYS SAT OUT, SOUGHT OUT
ENGAGING ACTIVITIES IN SUPPORT OF HER NEIGHBORHOOD
AND COMMUNITY. SHE SERVED FOR TWO TERMS AS THE
PRESIDENT OF RUSSIAN HELD NEIGHBORS SHAPING THE NOW 45
YEAR OLD NEIGHBORHOOD ASSOCIATION.
IN MANY WAYS REFLECTING ON HER SERVICE WITH RUSSIAN HILL
NEIGHBORS, ONE BOARD MEMBER OFFERED THIS QUOTE FROM THE
START SHE STOOD OUT. THE VIBRANT REDHEAD WITH
COLORFUL CLOTHES AND BOLD NECKLACES WHO WAS ALWAYS
IN MOTION. >> SHE ENCOURAGED ME TO TAKE ON
A LARGER ROLE IN THE ORGANIZATION AND ENCOURAGED MY
THOUGHTS AND IDEAS. TINA SEEMED TO KNOW EVERYONE
IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD AND CITY AND ALWAYS KNEW WHO TO CONTACT
TO GET THINGS DONE. ANOTHER BOARD MEMBER SHARED
THIS STORY OF TINA'S EAGERNESS TO IMPROVE HER COMMUNITY.
QUOTE I FIRST MET TINA AND MIKE AT A RUSSIAN HILL NEIGHBOR
COMMUNITY MEETING. I WAS THEN PRESIDENT AND WE PUT
OUT A CALL FOR VOLUNTEER VOLUNTEERS.
TINA'S HAND POPPED UP QUICKLY. MUCH TO MIKE'S DISMAY, IT SEEMS
THAT TINA WAS ALWAYS QUICK TO JUMP IN AND HELP.
THERE WAS SUCH A POWERFUL FORCE IN THAT LITTLE PACKAGE.
WHAT A GIFT. BOTH SHE AND MIKE WERE TO OUR
ORGANIZATION. I'LL ALWAYS REMEMBER HER
VITALITY AND SPIRIT. SUCH A BLESSING TO ALL WHO KNEW
HER AND QUOTE. I SAW THIS VITALITY IN SPIRIT
AND TINA AS WELL. WHEN I FIRST SOUGHT OUT HER
ADVICE AND EXPERTISE, I WAS A NEWLY ELECTED PRESIDENT OF
NORTH BEACH NEIGHBORS. EAGER TO LEARN FROM HER SERVICE
AND UNITE OUR NEIGHBORHOODS. SHE WAS GENEROUS, KIND
AND WARM. RUSSIAN HILL DISTRICT THREE
IN ALL OF SAN FRANCISCO ARE LUCKY TO HAVE BENEFITED FROM
HER SERVICE AND HER SPIRIT. BLESSINGS AND STRENGTH TO THEIR
FAMILY AND MAY SHE REST IN PEACE AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR SAUTER. MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR 230
SPECIAL ORDER. >> YES IT IS NOW TIME FOR THE
SPECIAL ORDER AT 230 RECOGNITION OF COMMENDATION FOR
MERITORIOUS SERVICE TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> AND I THINK THAT TODAY WE HAVE JUST DISTRICT TWO
SUPERVISOR CHERYL. >> OOP, THERE WE GO.
THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MANDEL MEN AND COLLEAGUES TODAY.
I AM VERY HONORED TO COMMEND THE CANINES COMPANIONS SAN
FRANCISCO SOUTH BAY CHAPTER IN RECOGNITION OF NATIONAL
SERVICE DOG MONTH AND DAVE AND ANYONE WITH YOU.
>> WOULD YOU PLEASE COME UP TO THE PODIUM WITH OUR FRIENDS?
>> MOST IMPORTANTLY, OUR FRIENDS.
HERE WE GO. ALL RIGHT.
FOR THE RECORD, THESE ARE OFFICIAL SERVICE DOGS.
SO SO PLEASE. >> RIGHT HERE.
RIGHT HERE. ALL RIGHT.
SINCE 1975, CANINE COMPANIONS HAS LED THE SERVICE DOG
INDUSTRY PROVIDING EXPERTLY TRAINED DOGS FREE OF CHARGE TO
ADULTS, CHILDREN AND VETERANS WITH DISABILITIES AS WELL AS
FACILITY DOGS TO PROFESSIONALS IN HEALTH CARE, EDUCATION
AND CRIMINAL JUSTICE. >> THE SAN FRANCISCO SOUTH BAY
CHAPTER FOUNDED IN 1993, SUPPORTS THIS MISSION LOCALLY
BY RAISING AWARENESS, RECRUITING VOLUNTEERS
AND FOSTERING COMMUNITY. ACROSS SANTA CLARA SANTA CRUZ,
SAN MATEO AND SAN FRANCISCO COUNTIES AND WITH US TODAY ARE
ARE THERE. I THINK I SEE MORE THAN 4 OR 4
PUPPIES IN TRAINING AND ONE SERVICE DOG THAT I CAN'T GET
THOSE NUMBERS RIGHT. THERE WE GO.
ALL RIGHT. REPRESENTING THE INDEPENDENCE
AND THE JOY THAT CANINE COMPANIONS BRINGS TO THOUSANDS
OF LIVES NATIONWIDE. >> IN A MOMENT WE'LL BE HEARING
FROM ANGELA KRAMER WHO SERVES AS A GRADUATE COORDINATOR FOR
THE CHAPTER. ANGELA IS ALSO THE FACILITATOR
FOR HER MOM VICKI WHO IS HERE WITH HER SERVICE DOG NAPOLEON
WHERE THERE'S NO YOU. AFTER EXPERIENCING A DOUBLE
BRAIN ANEURYSM, VICKI WAS UNABLE TO WALK FOR FIVE YEARS
BUT WITH NAPOLEONS PARTNERSHIP AND ESPECIALLY WITH ANGELA'S
SUPPORT SHE HAS REGAINED GREATER INDEPENDENCE
AND QUALITY OF LIFE. AND VICKI, WE ARE SO PROUD
AND HAPPY TO HAVE YOU HERE WITH US TODAY.
>> WE'RE ALSO JOINED BY SOME DEDICATED PUPPY RAISERS.
WE'VE GOT DAVE LASKER HERE WITH SWAZI CATHY.
CATHY GERVAIS HERE WITH BRET MEREDITH ALEXANDER WITH EDISON
AND DAVE LAIR WITH MINA. >> I WANT TO GIVE DAVE LASKER
ESPECIALLY RESIDENT OF CATHEDRAL HILL AND A SPECIAL
SPECIAL THANK YOU FOR ORGANIZING THIS TODAY AND ALSO
FOR ORGANIZING THE GET TOGETHER .
WE HAD THAT I THINK I SAW QUITE A FEW OF YOU AT EARLIER THESE
VOLUNTEERS YOU ALL ARE AT THE HEART OF THE CANINE COMPANIONS
MISSION PREPARING FUTURE SERVICE DOGS TO REALLY
TRANSFORM LIVES. ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS, I REALLY WANT TO THANK ALL OF YOU INDIVIDUALLY
AND CANINE COMPANION AS A WHOLE LOCAL CHAPTER AND OUR FURRY
GUESTS TODAY FOR THEIR COMPASSION, DEDICATION
AND SERVICE TO OUR COMMUNITY. >> CONGRATULATIONS.
AND THE FLOOR IS YOURS. HE'S MY NAME IS ANGELA AND THIS
IS MY MOM VICTORIOUS VICKI. AND I'M HONORED TO BE HERE
TODAY TO SHARE OUR JOURNEY WITH CANINE COMPANIONS AND A VERY
SPECIAL SERVICE DOG NAPOLEON THE THIRD NAPOLEON.
>> AND THIS IS NAPOLEON THE THIRD WHO HAS COMPLETELY
CHANGED OUR LIVES ARE ON MOTHER'S DAY IN 2013 MY MOM
VICKY SUFFERED A DOUBLE BRAIN ANEURYSM AT THE AGE OF 56.
IT WAS A DEVASTATING MOMENT BUT MY HUSBAND AND I MADE THE
DECISION TO A LIFE CHANGING DECISION TO MOVE HER IN WITH US
IN THE OUTER RICHMOND IN SAN FRANCISCO FOR MORE THAN SIX
YEARS MY MOM WAS WHEELCHAIR BOUND AND FOR THREE AND A HALF
YEARS SHE WAS NONVERBAL. >> TODAY I'M BEYOND PROUD TO
SAY MY MOM IS A WALKING TALKING MIRACLE.
>> THANK YOU TO PMC DAVIES AND SF STATE SPEECH THERAPY
PROGRAM WHO HELPED GET MY MOM BACK?
>> I'VE BEEN HER FULL TIME CAREGIVER FOR 12 YEARS AND IT
HASN'T BEEN EASY BUT IT'S BEEN ONE OF THE GREATEST HONORS OF
MY LIFE TO WALK ALONGSIDE AS SHE'S CONQUERED MOUNTAIN AFTER
MOUNTAIN IN JANUARY OF 2020 WE WERE GIFTED NAPOLEON THE THIRD
COMPLETELY FREE OF CHARGE FROM CANINE COMPANIONS.
AND WHEN I SAY HE'S CHANGED OUR LIVES I MEAN IT.
NAPOLEON PICKS UP FROM THE FLOOR ITEMS FROM THE FLOOR
OPENS DOORS AND ALSO MOST OF ALL HE MOTIVATES MY MOM TO WALK
EVERY DAY THROUGHOUT THE STREETS OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> WHEN NAPOLEON FIRST JOINED OUR FAMILY, MY MOM COULD ONLY
TAKE 20 STEPS WITH HER WALKER BEFORE NEEDING TO REST.
>> TODAY SHE'S WALKING THREE MILES A DAY WITH JUST A CANE.
LIVING WITH A DISABILITY IS CHALLENGING BUT AT TIMES DEEPLY
ISOLATING. >> BUT NAPOLEON HAS BEEN MORE
THAN JUST A SERVICE DOG. HE'S BEEN A BRIDGE TO THE
WORLD. PEOPLE STOP TO TALK, TO SMILE
AND CONNECT BECAUSE OF HIM WE FEEL LUCKY TO LIVE IN SAN
FRANCISCO A CITY THAT'S NOT ONLY LEADING THE CHARGE OF
ACCESSIBILITY AND ADA IMPROVEMENTS BUT IS ALSO
RECOGNIZING THE LIFE CHANGING IMPACT OF SERVICE DOGS.
>> SO TODAY WE'RE GRATEFUL TO CELEBRATE SAN FRANCISCO'S
PROCLAMATION OF SEPTEMBER AS SERVICE DOG MONTH.
AND IF YOU SEE US WALKING AROUND THE CITY, PLEASE STOP TO
SAY HI AND ON BEHALF OF OUR FAMILY.
AND THANKS TO CANINE COMPANIONS AND NAPOLEON THE THIRD.
AND TO ALL WHO ARE WORKING TO MAKE SAN FRANCISCO BETTER
AND MORE INCLUSIVE PLACE FOR ALL.
>> THANK YOU. I'M DOCTOR MEREDITH ALEXANDER.
I HAD A HEARING LAST YEAR AND I HAD AND I WAS SUFFERING FOR
QUITE OKAY. YOU GUYS NEED TO COME TO THE
MARKET FOR ONE ONE. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU KNOW LOTS OF THEM, RIGHT?
YES GREAT THANK YOU AGAIN. ALL RIGHT MADAM CLERK LET'S GO
BACK TO ROLL CALL. BUT I THINK WE SHOULD START
WITH SUPERVISOR WALTON AND COME BACK TO SUPERVISOR CHERYL.
THANK YOU SO MUCH. PRESIDENT MERRIMAN.
COLLEAGUES, TODAY I HAVE A RESOLUTION A COUPLE OF EXTERNAL
BOARD UPDATES IN MEMORIAM ON JULY 29TH, 2025, THE U.S.
ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY PROPOSED RESCINDING THE 2009
GREENHOUSE GAS ENDANGERMENT FINDING WHICH HAS BEEN THE
LEGAL AND SCIENTIFIC FOUNDATION FOR REGULATING GREENHOUSE GAS
EMISSIONS FOR MORE THAN 15 YEARS FOLLOWING EXTENSIVE
SCIENTIFIC REVIEW AND MORE THAN 380,000 PUBLIC COMMENTS.
THE EPA CONCLUDED THAT SIX MAJOR GREENHOUSE GASES POSE A
CLEAR DANGER TO CURRENT AND FUTURE GENERATIONS.
THE FINDING HAS SINCE UNDERPINNED VEHICLE EMISSION
STANDARDS AND OTHER CLIMATE PROTECTIONS AND HAS BEEN
REPEATEDLY UPHELD IN FEDERAL COURT.
RESCINDING IT NOW WOULD STRIP THE ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION
AGENCY OF AUTHORITY TO REGULATE GREENHOUSE GAS EMISSIONS FROM
MOTOR VEHICLES, ELIMINATE MANUFACTURER OBLIGATIONS TO
MEASURE AND REPORT EMISSIONS AND UNDERMINE DECADES OF
PROGRESS ON CLEAN AIR AND CLIMATE POLICY.
TRANSPORTATION REMAINS THE LARGEST SOURCE OF EMISSIONS
AND A SIGNIFICANT SOURCE OF COAL POLLUTANTS THAT
DISPROPORTIONATELY HARM LOW INCOME COMMUNITIES
AND COMMUNITIES OF COLOR. >> SAN FRANCISCO HAS LONG
CHAMPIONED CLIMATE ACTION AND AIR QUALITY PROTECTIONS
AND WE CANNOT ALLOW FEDERAL BACKSLIDING.
>> I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISORS SUTTER CHIN AND FIELDER FOR
YOUR EARLY CO-SPONSORSHIP. WE ALSO HEARD FROM SUPERVISOR
MAHMUD WHO GAVE AN UPDATE ON THE AIR DISTRICT.
BUT I DO JUST WANT TO ADD THAT THE AIR DISTRICT IS MODERNIZING
INSPECTIONS THROUGH A NEW TARGETED INSPECTION PROGRAM
THAT PRIORITIZES ENVIRONMENTAL JUSTICE AND COMMUNITY INPUT
PILOTED IN BAYVIEW HUNTERS POINT SINCE MARCH.
THE PROGRAM HAS FOCUSED ON FACILITIES IDENTIFIED BY THE
ASSEMBLY BILL 617 COMMUNITY STEERING COMMITTEE.
RESULTING IN MULTIPLE NOTICES OF VIOLATION AND THE ADDITION
OF WEEKEND EXPRESSION USING NEW CRITERIA SUCH AS COMPLIANCE
HISTORY AND EMISSIONS INVENTORY .
THE DISTRICT INSPECTED 33 MORE FACILITIES ISSUING SEVEN
FURTHER VIOLATIONS TO PROTECT RESIDENTS FROM WILDFIRES SMOKE.
THE AIR DISTRICT IS ALSO ENCOURAGING THE PUBLIC TO SIGN
UP FOR SPARE THE AIR ALERTS AND SPARE THE AIR FORCE.
ALSO JUST REPORTING ON THE JOINT POWERS BOARD FOR
CALTRAIN, CALTRAIN HAS SEEN A 75% INCREASE IN RIDERSHIP
BETWEEN JULY 2024 AND JULY 20TH, 25.
CALTRAIN IS SERVING OVER A MILLION RIDERS MONTHLY
AND WEEKEND RIDERSHIP IS THE HIGHEST IT HAS EVER BEEN
ESPECIALLY WHEN RIDERSHIP IS INCREASING AS WELL AS CALTRAIN
LEANED INTO PARTNERSHIPS WITH ENTITIES SUCH AS THE GIANTS
ORACLE, STANFORD AND SAP CENTER.
CALTRAIN HAS ALSO BEEN CREATING TEAM TRAINS FOR CONCERTS WHICH
IS GENERATING POSITIVE COVERAGE OF THE AGENCY AND GETTING NEW
RIDERS TO CHECK IT OUT. CALTRAIN HAS A STRONG BRAND
WITH OVER 91% FAVOURABILITY RATING FROM RIDERS ALTHOUGH THE
RIDERSHIP TREND IS OUTSTANDING IT'S STILL LOWER THAN 2019
LEVELS. APPROXIMATELY 65% GIVEN THE
HIGH BAR HIGH FARE BOX RATIO THAT CALTRAIN USED TO DEPEND ON
70 PER 75% OF THE BUDGET FROM FARES.
CALTRAIN HAS AN OPERATING DEFICIT THAT WILL HIT THE
BUDGET FISCAL YEAR 27. >> CALTRAIN IS SUPPORTIVE OF SB
63 WHICH WOULD HELP CLOSE THE PENDING OPERATING DEFICIT IF IT
IS SUCCESSFUL. CALTRAIN IS ALSO IMPLEMENTING A
NON FARE STRATEGY TO LOOK AT OPTIONS TO GENERATE REVENUE
SUCH AS SELLING OR LEASING FIBER OPTIC CABLE ADVERTISING
AND OTHER PROJECTS TO DIVERSIFY THE AGENCY'S RESOURCES.
RECENTLY ONE OF THE LOCAL ENERGY PROVIDERS AGREED TO PAY
FOR THE ENERGY THAT THE NEW ELECTRIC TRAINS WERE SENDING
BACK TO THE GRID. CALTRAIN WILL RUN A BILL TO GET
THE SIMILAR TREATMENT FROM PIGEON AS WELL.
CALTRAIN CONTINUES TO WORK ON COST EFFICIENCY AND COST SAVING
STRATEGIES, CUTTING NEARLY $10 MILLION OUT OF THE BUDGET LAST
YEAR. TO SHOW THAT WE ARE TIGHTENING
OUR BELT SEPTEMBER SAFETY MONTH AN AGENCY WILL CONTINUE TO ROLL
OUT IMPROVEMENTS THAT INCREASE SAFETY.
THE LATEST EFFORTS HAVE BEEN USING AIR TECHNOLOGY AS A TOOL
TO HELP US LEARN WHAT IS HAPPENING AT CROSSINGS AND TO
MAKE MODIFICATIONS. LASTLY, I HAVE AN IN MEMORIAM
HONORING THE LIFE AND LEGACY OF SAMUEL MURRAY A MAN WHOSE FAITH
SERVICE AND LOVE FOR COMMUNITY TOUCHED COUNTLESS LIVES.
SAMUEL MURRAY WAS BORN ON SEPTEMBER 19TH, 1952 IN SAN
FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA TO LEE ENDORSED MURRAY.
>> HE MADE HISTORY AS THE FIRST AFRICAN-AMERICAN STUDENT TO
INTEGRATE JUSTICE IN A HIGH SCHOOL IN NAPA VALLEY IN THE
LATE 1960S A REFLECTION OF THE COURAGE AND TRAILBLAZING SPIRIT
THAT WILL GUIDE HIS LIFE. SAMUEL DEVOTED HIS CAREER TO
PROGRAM DEVELOPMENT, OUTREACH, ADVOCACY AND COMMUNITY
ORGANIZING. ALWAYS WITH THE FOCUS ON
UPLIFTING POPULATIONS AT RISK. A PROUD MEMBER OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO BAYVIEW HUNTERS POINT ROTARY CLUB HE BROUGHT THE SAME
DEDICATION TO SERVICE THAT MARKED HIS PERSONAL
AND PROFESSIONAL LIFE. >> HE LATER PURSUED HIS DEGREE
IN BIBLICAL STUDIES AT TRINITY COLLEGE.
GROUNDING HIS WORK AND FAITH IN SCRIPTURE.
>> A DEVOTED BELIEVER IN JESUS CHRIST.
SAMUEL WAS AN ACTIVE MEMBER AND ELDER AT LORD'S FELLOWSHIP
WHERE HE FAITHFULLY TAUGHT BIBLE STUDIES.
KNOWN FOR HIS TRADEMARK ENCOURAGEMENT, YOU GOT TO MAKE
IT PERSONAL. HE INSPIRED MANY BY HANDING OUT
MIRRORS, BOOKS AND EVEN SNACKS DURING HIS LESSONS.
HE ALSO ORGANIZED THE ANNUAL PRAYER BREAKFAST A CHURCH
GATHERING THAT UNITED PEOPLE FROM ACROSS RELIGIOUS
TRADITIONS TO PRAY FOR THE CITY.
WE RECOGNIZE SAM AS A TRAILBLAZER, A MAN OF DEEP
FAITH AND A SERVANT LEADER WHOSE COMMITMENT TO COMMUNITY
CONTINUES TO INSPIRE. HIS LEGACY OF BREAKING
BARRIERS, LIFTING OTHERS AND LIVING WITH PURPOSE WILL
FOREVER REMAIN A GUIDING LIGHT FOR SAN FRANCISCO AND BEYOND.
>> THE REST I SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WALTON SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU.
COLLEAGUES, I WILL REPORT BACK ON OUR SITE BORE DUTIES AND FOR
ME ONE IS THE FREE CITY COLLEGE OVERSIGHTS COMMITTEE.
EARLIER THE YEAR PRIOR TO BUDGET THE COMMITTEE HAS MADE A
SERIES OF RECOMMENDATIONS SPECIFICALLY ABOUT FREE CITY
COLLEGE REIMBURSE AMENDS PROCESS AND ALSO BUDGET TO NOT
JUST INCLUDE TO TO INCREASE THE DOLLAR AMOUNT FROM THE EXISTING
MOU TO ALSO COVER STUDENT FEES. >> WE HOPE TO CONTINUE THIS
MOMENTUM AND THAT WE LOOK FORWARD TO WORK WITH CITY
COLLEGE OF SAN FRANCISCO WHICH NOW THEY HAVE A NEW CHANCELLOR
AND HER NAME IS DR. KIMBERLY MESSINA.
AND SO WE LOOK FORWARD TO WORKING WITH HER TO EXPAND FREE
CITY AND ALSO TO MAKE SURE IT REALLY IS A PROGRAM THAT WORKS
AND DELIVER FOR SAN FRANCISCANS AND THAT IS THE WORK THAT IS
COMING IN THE FALL TO REEVALUATE THE EXISTING MEMO
YOU TO SEE HOW WE CAN BETTER THE MOU NEXT I AM ALSO ON THE
STATE LEGISLATION COMMITTEE WE BEEN WITH I BEEN ON THIS
COMMITTEE WE PRESENT AMENDMENT IT WAS A WE DID NOT HAVE ANY
THE AUGUST POSITIONS BECAUSE THE STATE LEGISLATURE WERE ON
RECESS AND NOW THEY JUST RETURNING SO I HOPE TO MORE
TRUE REPORT OUR NEXT MEETING WILL BE ON SEPTEMBER 20TH OF.
>> BUT GENERALLY SPEAKING SHOULD LOOK OUT FOR THE AGENDA
THAT TYPICALLY POSTS IT FOR A DELIGHT TO STATE LEGISLATION
COMMITTEE WE'VE BEEN RELYING ON OUR STATE LOBBYIST TO TRACK ON
OUR BEHALF THE ONE THAT WE CAN SO WALMART MORE TO REPORT BACK.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHEN
SUPERVISOR CHEN SUBMIT THANK YOU SUPERVISOR DORSEY.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES, I'M HONORED TO BRING FORWARD A RESOLUTION THAT
I THINK WILL COMPLEMENT SUPERVISOR MEL GARS RECOGNITION
OF TRANSIT MONTH. IT WILL DECLARE SEPTEMBER 2025
AS MUNI HERITAGE MONTH IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO FOR 113 YEARS MUNI HAS SERVED AS A LIFELINE FOR
OUR COMMUNITIES AND A DEFINING PART OF SAN FRANCISCO'S
IDENTITY FROM ITS FIRST BUS ROUTE LAUNCHED ON SEPTEMBER
FIRST, 1917, MUNI HELPED PIONEER PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION
IN AMERICA AS THE FIRST MUNICIPALLY OWNED SYSTEM OF ITS
KIND IN ANY MAJOR U.S. CITY OVER THE DECADES MUNI HAS BEEN
A NATIONAL LEADER IN INNOVATION INTRODUCING ZERO EMISSION
TROLLEY BUSSES, EXPANDING ACCESSIBLE TRANSPORTATION
AND BRINGING PUBLIC ART INTO EVERYDAY COMMUTES.
IT HAS ALSO CHAMPIONED THE ADVANCEMENT OF CIVIL RIGHTS
EQUITY FOR WOMEN OPERATORS AS FAR BACK AS WORLD WAR TWO
SUPPORTING LGBTQ PLUS INCLUSIVE WORKPLACE POLICIES YEARS BEFORE
OTHER CITIES DID SO AND LAUNCHING FARE EQUITY
PROGRAMS THAT MAKE TRANSIT ACCESSIBLE TO ALL.
NONE OF THIS WOULD BE POSSIBLE WITHOUT THE GENERATIONS OF MUNI
WORKERS, OPERATORS, ENGINEERS, MECHANICS, CLEANERS AND STATION
AGENTS WHO'VE KEPT THE CITY RUNNING THROUGH GOOD TIMES
AND THROUGH BAD AND WHO CONTINUE TO CONNECT OUR
NEIGHBORHOODS EVERY DAY. WE'RE ALSO INCREDIBLY FORTUNATE
FOR THE ONGOING PARTNERSHIP BETWEEN US OF MTA AND THE
MARKET STREET RAILWAY WHO'VE HELPED PRESERVE THE HISTORIC
STREETCARS AND CABLE CARS THAT ARE NOT ONLY BELOVED SYMBOLS OF
OUR CITY BUT LIVING REMINDERS OF OUR TRANSIT LEGACY.
THAT PARTNERSHIP WILL BE ON FULL DISPLAY DURING MUNI
HERITAGE WEEKEND ON SEPTEMBER 20TH AND 21ST.
>> FIRST A JOYFUL CELEBRATION OF THE PAST, PRESENT AND FUTURE
OF PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION IN SAN FRANCISCO WITH THIS RESOLUTION
WHICH HAS BEEN A LABOR OF LOVE AND ONE EXAMPLE OF THE GREAT
WORK DONE BY MY SUMMER INTERN TOMMY LAGUARDIA WE AFFIRM OUR
APPRECIATION FOR MORE THAN A CENTURY OF DEDICATED SERVICE
AND WE RECOMMIT OURSELVES TO A FUTURE WHERE PUBLIC TRANSIT
REMAINS FAST, FREQUENT, RELIABLE, SAFE AND CLEAN
AND ALSO TRULY REFLECTS SAN FRANCISCO'S VALUE OF VALUES OF
SUSTAINABILITY AND INCLUSION. NOW FOR UPDATES FROM MY OUTSIDE
BOARDS AND COMMISSIONS I SERVE ON THE BAY CONSERVATION
AND DEVELOPMENT COMMISSION OR BCCDC WHERE WE HAVE HAD A
PRODUCTIVE FEW MONTHS. WE APPROVED SEVERAL LARGE
PROJECTS AND PROJECT PERMITS REGION WIDE INCLUDING TWO
EXCITING SAN FRANCISCO PROJECTS .
FIRST THE COMMISSION HELD A PUBLIC HEARING AND VOTED
UNANIMOUSLY TO APPROVE AN AMENDMENT TO THE SAN FRANCISCO
WATERFRONT SPECIAL AREA PLAN THAT WILL ALLOW FOR DEVELOPMENT
IN FISHERMAN'S WHARF TO MATCH THE NORTHEASTERN WATERFRONT.
THIS WILL ALLOW NEW OPPORTUNITIES FOR THE AREA
AND ALSO ESTABLISH A SEA LEVEL RISE PUBLIC EDUCATION PROGRAM
TO BE MANAGED BY THE EXPLORATORIUM AS A PUBLIC
BENEFIT. I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR
SAUTER AND HIS OFFICE FOR THEIR LEADERSHIP ON THAT.
THANKS AS WELL TO PORT STAFF FOR THEIR WORK IN COLLABORATION
WITH BCCDC AND THE COMMUNITY ON THOSE UPDATES.
SECOND, THE COMMISSION VOTED ON AN APPLICATION FOR INDIAN INDIA
BASIN SHORELINE PARK PROJECT TO REDEVELOP, EXPAND AND ENHANCE
THE EXISTING INDIA BASIN SHORELINE WITH A 7.48 ACRE AREA
FOR RECREATIONAL AND PUBLIC ACCESS USES ALONG THE INDIA
BASINS SHORELINE. KUDOS TO SUPERVISOR WALTON
AND HIS OFFICE FOR THEIR LEADERSHIP ON THAT PROJECT
AND THANKS AS WELL TO OUR RECREATION AND PARK DEPARTMENT
FOR THEIR WORK WITH BKD AND THE COMMUNITY BEYOND OUR OWN CITY'S
BORDERS. WE ALSO APPROVED A REQUEST FROM
CALTRANS AND MTC TO TEST NEW TRANSPORTATION OPTIONS BETWEEN
THE NORTH AND EAST BAY TO IMPROVE TRANSIT ACCESS FOR
PUBLIC ACCESS TO THE RICHMOND SAN RAFAEL BRIDGE.
THE EAST BAY REGIONAL PARK'S RESTORATION OF THE HAYWARD
MARSH SYSTEM AND A COUPLE OF OTHER PROJECTS ON THE
ASSOCIATION FOR BAY AREA GOVERNMENTS OR ABEG.
WE MET ONCE SINCE THE LAST UPDATE.
OUR JULY MEETING WAS MOSTLY INFORMATIONAL WITH UPDATES ON
THE STATE BUDGET INCLUDING THE GOVERNOR'S COMMITMENTS TO
TRANSIT FUNDING AND AFFORDABLE HOUSING INVESTMENTS.
WE ALSO RECOMMENDED ADVANCEMENTS OF THE FINAL
BLUEPRINT FOR PLANNED BAY AREA 2050 PLUS TO THE SEQUEL
PROCESS. THE FINAL BLUEPRINT INCLUDES
UPDATES TO BASELINE DATA SUCH AS TRANSIT SERVICE LEVELS
AND EQUITY PRIORITY COMMUNITIES PLANNING ASSUMPTIONS SUCH AS
LEVEL OF HYBRID WORK AND FORECASTS FOR FUTURE FUTURE
POPULATION AND JOBS AND GROWTH GEOGRAPHIES WHERE FUTURE
HOUSING AND JOBS WILL BE FOCUSED ON THE REENTRY COUNCIL
WHICH MEETS QUARTERLY STAFF PROVIDED UPDATES FROM THE
DIRECT SERVICES LEGISLATION POLICY AND PRACTICES
SUBCOMMITTEES. THE COUNCIL ALSO HEARD A
PRESENTATION ON REENTRY SERVICES COORDINATION FROM THE
FOUNDERS OF DIGNIFY, A COMPANY THAT USES TECHNOLOGY TO SUPPORT
INCARCERATED PEOPLE AS THEY ADJUST TO STABILIZE RVS AFTER
REENTRY. AND FINALLY ON THE HEALTH
SERVICE BOARD. THERE ARE NO MAJOR UPDATES TO
REPORT SINCE WE LAST HEARD FROM HHS DURING OUR BUDGET PROCESS.
HOWEVER, EVERYONE SHOULD BE AWARE THAT OPEN ENROLLMENT IS
COMING UP SO PLEASE BE SURE TO MARK YOUR CALENDARS FOR THE
OPEN ENROLLMENT DATES FOR THE 2026 PLAN YEAR WHICH WILL BEGIN
ON WEDNESDAY OCTOBER 1ST AND END ON FRIDAY OCTOBER 24TH.
DON'T MISS IT AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU SUPERVISOR DORSEY SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO.
GOOD AFTERNOON COLLEAGUES. >> I WANT TO SHARE RECENT
UPDATES FROM THE GOLDEN GATE BRIDGE AND HIGHWAY
TRANSPORTATION DISTRICT AS PART OF THE MTC'S REGIONAL EFFORTS
TO COORDINATE THE BAY AREA'S TRANSIT AGENCY SCHEDULES.
THE DISTRICT'S BUS AND FERRY SERVICE GOLDEN GATE TRANSIT IS
PROPOSING SIGNIFICA AT SERVICE ADJUSTMENTS THIS SEPTEMBER AS
PART OF THE MARIN SONOMA COORDINATED TRANSIT SERVICE.
ALSO KNOWN AS MASCOTS, THE MASCOTS PLAN WAS DEVELOPED
IN COLLABORATION WITH NORTH BAY TRANSIT PARTNERS INCLUDING
SMART MARIN TRANSIT, SONOMA COUNTY TRANSIT, PETALUMA
TRANSIT, THE MTC AND OTHERS TO ALIGN WITH CHANGING TRAVEL
PATTERNS ALONG THE HIGHWAY ONE ON ONE CORRIDOR.
PROPOSED CHANGES REFLECT SHIFTS IN RIDERSHIP DUE TO THE
INTRODUCTION OF SMART RAIL COVID 19 TRAVEL BEHAVIOR
CHANGES AND A RENEWED PUSH TO IMPROVE REGIONAL TRANSIT
INTEGRATION. GIVEN THE SCARCITY OF TRANSIT
FUNDING AVAILABLE FROM THE STATE AND FEDS, THESE EFFORTS
WILL HELP REINVEST FUNDS TO ALIGN WITH RIDER DEMAND
INCLUDING MORE FREQUENT SERVICE BETWEEN SAN RAFAEL AND SAN
FRANCISCO. THE BRIDGE DISTRICT REPORTS
THAT 70% OF GOLDEN GATE BRIDGE TRAVEL STARTS OR ENDS SOUTH OF
SAN RAFAEL AND 75% OF SAN FRANCISCO BOUND RIDERS ARE
HEADED TO DOWNTOWN SAN FRANCISCO AND THE NORTHEAST
QUADRANT OF THE CITY FOR THE BRIDGE DISTRICT.
THIS FINANCIAL STRATEGY FOCUSES ON REALLOCATING UNDER UTILIZED
SERVICE TO IMPROVE HIGH DEMAND CORRIDORS.
COORDINATED OUTREACH TO NORTH BAY TRANSIT AGENCY STAKEHOLDERS
BEGAN EARLIER THIS YEAR. HOWEVER, SOME CORE BRIDGE
DISTRICT STAKEHOLDERS INCLUDING ATU LOCAL 1575 HAVE SHARED
THEIR CONCERNS AND FRUSTRATIONS WITH THE LACK OF ALTERNATIVES
AND THE OVERALL PACE OF THIS REGIONAL TRANSIT SYSTEM
REALIGNMENT INCLUDING FORCED TRANSFERS, FEWER DIRECT ROUTES
,LOSS OF KEY CONNECTIONS, ECONOMIC IMPACTS AND EQUITY
CONCERNS. THE FIRST PUBLIC HEARING ON THE
PROPOSED ROUTE CHANGES WAS HELD IN AUGUST AND PUBLIC REVIEW
WILL CONTINUE THIS MONTH. THE BRIDGE BOARD IS EXPECTED TO
MAKE FINAL DECISIONS BY THE END OF SEPTEMBER WITH
IMPLEMENTATION PLAN FOR SPRING 2026 IN COORDINATION WITH
REGIONAL TRANSIT PARTNERS AND OTHER BRIDGE DISTRICT NEWS.
BRIDGE TRAFFIC BUS RIDERSHIP AND FERRY RIDERSHIP CONTINUES
TO GROW YEAR AFTER YEAR. THE DISTRICT HAS CONTINUOUSLY
EVALUATED RIDERSHIP TRENDS AND ADJUSTING BUS AND FERRY
TRANSIT SERVICE SCHEDULES IN ORDER TO MEET DEMAND.
THE BRIDGE DISTRICT IS ALSO WORKING TO ADDRESS YEARS OF
CHRONIC UNDERPERFORMANCE OF ITS RETIREMENT PLAN FOR BUS
OPERATORS OVER THE PAST DECADE. POOR INVESTMENT RETURNS
CONTRIBUTED TO RETIREMENT PLAN LOSSES TOTALING NEARLY $24
MILLION TODAY. THE BRIDGE DISTRICT'S
RETIREMENT PLAN IS JUST 47% FUNDED WITH AN UNFUNDED
LIABILITY TOTALING 105 MILLION. COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM
INTRODUCING A LONG OVERDUE RESOLUTION TO RECOGNIZE THE
DISTRICT FOR THE PLAYA VILLAGE NEIGHBORHOOD ITS RESIDENTS
AND BROADER COMMUNITY FOR ITS HISTORICAL, ARCHITECTURAL
AND CULTURAL IMPACT. WHILE MANY MAY THINK OF THIS
AREA AS THE QUAINT LAID BACK BEACHY NEIGHBORHOOD AT THE
TERMINUS OF THE NW DUE TO TURNAROUND, I AM PROUD TO
HIGHLIGHT AND CELEBRATE THIS COMMUNITY'S 100 PLUS YEARS OF
GRASSROOTS ACTION TRANSFORMING UNDERUTILIZED PUBLIC SPACES
INTO PUBLIC COMMUNITY BENEFIT FROM THE CONVERSION OF 1800S
CABLE CARS INTO HOMES IN THE EARLY 1900S TO HISTORIC SMALL
BUSINESSES TO THE NEIGHBORHOODS COMMITMENT TO CREATE LA PLAYA
PARK. I AM PROUD TO RECOGNIZE THE
SIGNIFICANCE OF LA PLAYA VILLAGE ON DISTRICT FOR
ARTISTIC AND BEACHSIDE CULTURE. I ENCOURAGE RESIDENTS
AND VISITORS TO RIDE THE N JUDA TO THE END OF THE LINE SO YOU
CAN EXPERIENCE THIS NEIGHBORHOOD FOR YOURSELVES
AND SADLY TODAY I ASK THAT WE ADJOURN THIS MEETING IN MEMORY
OF FATHER EDWARD EDDIE REECE WHO PASSED AWAY ON AUGUST 2ND
AFTER A BRIEF BATTLE WITH PANCREATIC CANCER.
FATHER REECE WAS 82 YEARS OLD AND FOR THE PAST NINE YEARS HE
SERVED AS THE PRESIDENT OF ST IGNATIUS COLLEGE PREP.
BUT HIS LEGACY AND COMMITMENT TO EDUCATE OUR YOUTH SPANS
DECADES FOR 54 YEARS. FATHER REESE DEDICATED HIS LIFE
AS A JESUIT HIGH SCHOOL TEACHER AND ADMINISTRATOR SERVING AT
SIX DIFFERENT SCHOOLS. FATHER REESE WAS BORN ON
OCTOBER 2ND, 1942 IN LOS ANGELES.
QUICKLY AFTER GRADUATING FROM LOYOLA HIGH SCHOOL OF LOS
ANGELES, HE BEGAN HIS MINISTRY IN EDUCATION.
HIS EARLY ASSIGNMENTS INCLUDED INCLUDED TEACHING HISTORY
AND ENGLISH AT LOYOLA HIGH SCHOOL WHERE HE LATER SERVED
IN SEVERAL ADMINISTRATIVE ROLES.
IN 1980 HE BECAME PRINCIPAL OF BELLARMINE COLLEGE PREPARATORY
IN SAN JOSE WHERE HE LED FOR 13 YEARS AND PIONEERED THE
INTEGRATION OF TECHNOLOGY INTO THE CURRICULUM DURING THE RISE
OF SILICON VALLEY. HIS MINISTRY ALSO TOOK HIM TO
SYDNEY, AUSTRALIA TO SACRAMENTO AND TO PHENIX, ARIZONA BEFORE
BECOMING THE 31ST PRESIDENT OF ST IGNATIUS HIGH SCHOOL.
>> FATHER QUICKLY MADE A PROFOUND IMPACT BY LAUNCHING
THE FATHER SAW ACADEMY WHICH GREW THE SCHOOL'S SCHOLARSHIP
ENDOWMENT. HE ALSO SPEARHEADED THE VISION
FOR THE NEW LEARNING COMMONS WHICH IS NOW UNDER
CONSTRUCTION. HIS LEADERSHIP HAD A
SIGNIFICANT IMPACT ON THE COMMUNITY OVER THE PAST TEN
YEARS WHICH WILL CONTINUE TO SHAPE GENERATIONS OF STUDENTS
IN THE YEARS TO COME. THROUGHOUT HIS 60 YEARS AS A
JESUIT FATHER, EDDIE WAS KNOWN NOT ONLY FOR HIS ADMINISTRATIVE
EXCELLENCE BUT HIS JOYFUL SPIRIT, SHARP WIT AND DEEP
PASTORAL CARE. HE OFTEN SAID IF YOU'RE NOT
HAVING FUN THEN WHAT ARE YOU DOING?
FATHER REECE'S FUNERAL WAS HELD ON AUGUST 20TH AT ST IGNATIUS
CHURCH AT THE UNIVERSITY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
HE IS SURVIVED BY HIS BROTHER. FATHER THOMAS J.
REESE OF WASHINGTON DC AND THE REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO SUPERVISOR CHERYL SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. SEEING NO NAMES ON THE ROSTER
THAT CONCLUDES THE INTRODUCTION OF NEW BUSINESS.
>> OKAY, LET'S GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT.
>> AT THIS TIME THE BOARD WELCOMES YOUR GENERAL PUBLIC
COMMENT. YOU CAN LINE UP ON THE RIGHT
HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER, YOUR RIGHT HAND SIDE.
YOU MAY SPEAK TO THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED.
ITEMS 12 THROUGH 16 ON THE ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE
REFERENCE CALENDAR OTHER GENERAL MATTERS THAT ARE NOT ON
THE PUBLISHED AGENDA BUT MUST BE WITHIN THE BOARD SUBJECT
MATTER JURISDICTION. WE'RE SETTING THE TIMER FOR TWO
MINUTES. JUST KEEP YOUR EYE ON THE TIMER
ON THE LECTERN THERE. >> MR. WASHINGTON, WE'LL START
WITH YOU. WELL, THANK YOU.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH. CLERK.
I JUST WANT TO SAY WELCOME BACK TO THIS RAT RACE HERE IN CITY
HALL BY THE BAY. I JUST WANT TO SAY I'M GOING TO
PUT A NOTICE TO THE ALL THE SUPERVISORS AND THE MAYOR AND
I'M GOING TO TRY TO DO THIS IN TWO MINUTES.
>> WE ARE IN A STATE OF EMERGENCY IN THE WEST
IN ADDITION TO AREA D FIVE HOWEVER YOU WANT TO CALL IT
DYSFUNCTION YOU KNOW, ALL UP AND DOWN THE FILLMORE ALL
IN THE COMMUNITY IS DYSFUNCTIONAL AND I DON'T HAVE
TIME TO NAME THEM. I COULD I START FROM SAFELY THE
ADDITION OF THIS SO MUCH. NOW WE GOT A HUGE CLOSING DOWN
THE CALL CENTER. >> WHAT THE IS GOING ON IN A
TWO AREA D FIVE? >> I KNOW IT AIN'T YOUR FAULT
BUT IT'S ON YOUR WATCH NOW AND I TALKED TO YOU, BY THE
WAY. >> CONGRATULATIONS ON YOUR
WEDDING. I DID THAT 50 YEARS AGO.
HA HA. IN THAT TO SHOW YOU HOW LONG
AGO. LET ME JUST SAY MY EXPERIENCE
HERE IS CITY HALL. IT GOES BACK DECADES.
THE ONLY ONE THAT THE CLARK'S BEEN HERE A LITTLE LONGER
AND DORSEY SAID HE'S BEEN HERE A LITTLE WHILE BUT NOBODY'S
BEEN IN THE SUPERVISORS CHAMBERS LONGER THAN ACE OWNED
THE CASE. I'VE BEEN HERE 30 SOMETHING
YEARS. I SHED SOME TEARS BUT I'M HERE
TO TELL YOU FOUGHT ONLY GOT A PETITION NOTICE OUT TO THE
MAYOR AND HIS SUPERVISORS. WE ARE IN A STATE OF EMERGENCY.
I NEED TO HAVE YOUR ATTENTION TO COME INTO THE FILLMORE.
YOU'VE BEEN PUT ON NOTICE. I GOT 30S AND I WILL BE PUTTING
IN WRITING. WE NEED ATTENTION IN THE FIELD
MORE WHEN I CALL IT THE FEEL. >> NO, NO.
BUT I'M TRYING TO PUT THE FEEL BACK IN THE MORE BUT I NEED
SOME HELP FROM THESE POLITICIANS.
>> POLITICS ARE FULL OF TRICKS. IT MAKES YOU TURN TO A LUNATIC
AND I'M NOT TRYING TO BE FACETIOUS BUT I'M TELLING Y'ALL
YOU PUT NO I'M PUTTING OUT ON NOTICE TODAY WE ARE IN A STATE
OF EMERGENCY IN THE FILLMORE. >> MY NAME IS ACE.
HUH? THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER I WISH WE WOULD SHOW A LITTLE R-E-S-P-E-C-T FOR
OUR PRESIDENT AND I WON'T MENTION ANY NAMES IN PARTICULAR
BUT I WOULD LIKE TO TALK ABOUT THIS REMARKABLE PROPHECY
AND DANIEL CHAPTER EIGHT AND VERSE 14 IT HAS TO DO WITH
1776 IN THE SPRING IT ENDED IN 1776.
THEN I HEARD ONE SAINT SPEAKING AND ANOTHER SAINT SAID UNDER
THAT CERTAIN SAINT WHICH SPAKE HOW LONG SHALL THE VISION
CONCERNING THE DAILY SACRIFICE AND THE TRANSGRESSION OF
DESOLATION TO GIVE BOTH THE SANCTUARY AND THE HOST TO BE
TRODDEN UNDERFOOT AND HE SAID UNTO ME UNDER 2003 HUNDRED DAYS
THEN SHE'LL THE SANCTUARY BE CLEANSED OR MADE RIGHTEOUS OR
JUSTIFIED I GUESS IT'S THE SAME HEBREW WORD WHEN SOLOMON PRAYED
AND SAID IN REGARDS TO JUSTIFYING THE RIGHTEOUS HE
SAID THEN HERE THOU IN HEAVEN AND DO AND JUDGE THY SERVANTS
CONDEMNED THE WICKED TO BRING HIS WAY UPON HIS HEAD
AND JUSTIFYING THE RIGHTEOUS TO GIVE HIM ACCORDING TO HIS
RIGHTEOUSNESS. NOW 2300 DAYS MEANS NOTHING
IN REGARDS TO A SOLAR LUNAR CYCLE BUT 2300 YEARS IS A VERY,
VERY PRECISE SOLAR LUNAR CYCLE THAT DANIEL OBVIOUSLY HAD NO
IDEA ABOUT. OKAY.
AND AND THERE WAS A GREEK ASTRONOMER NAMED MITNICK WHO
FOUND OUT EVERY 19 YEARS WITHIN A COUPLE HOURS YOU HAD THE
EXACT SAME YOU HAD A NEW MOON EVERY 19 YEARS AND THEN
COLUMBUS FOUND OUT A COUPLE OF HUNDRED YEARS AFTER THAT EVERY
70 SIX YEARS, 76 YEARS YOU WOULD HAVE A EVEN MORE PRECISE
ONE. >> BUT WHEN SOLOMON'S TEMPLE
WAS DESTROYED I WOULD I CAN PROVE IT.
IT WAS EXACTLY 2300 YEARS. OKAY.
WE ARE TO 1776. WE ARE SO BLESSED TO LIVE HERE.
OKAY START READING THE BIBLE REPENTANCE BELIEVE IN JESUS
CHRIST. THAT'S YOUR PROBLEM.
YOU NEED TO BELIEVE IN JESUS CHRIST.
>> HE DIED FOR YOUR SINS. HE RESURRECTED.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. LET'S WELCOME OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> PLEASE TELL MAMA JESUS IS COMING.
>> HE'S COMING BACK HE REALLY GOOD AFTERNOON BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS. FOR THE RECORD, MY NAME IS
CHRIS WARD KLEIN. I ALSO GO BY SERGEANT KLEIN OF
THE UNITED STATES MARINE CORPS. I'LL START WITH A QUOTE FROM
JAMES BALDWIN PEOPLE WHO ARE TRAPPED IN HISTORY AND HISTORY
IS TRAPPED IN THEM AND SAN FRANCISCO KNOWS THIS TOO WELL.
I HAVE A COPY OF AN FBI REPORT AND SUPPORTING EVIDENCE OF
HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO BY PEOPLE
IN SAN FRANCISCO. I AM REQUIRED BY LAW TO TURN
THIS OVER TO THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS TODAY WHICH I WILL
A HARD COPY. >> IT'S VERY CONCERNING, JUST
VERY CONCERNING AND WE HAD TO DO THIS BY THE BOOK BEFORE I
RE-ENLISTED INTO THE MARINE CORPS.
I KNEW SOMETHING WAS WRONG. I FILED A UNITED NATIONS HUMAN
RIGHTS REPORT. THEN I CONTACTED THE DEPARTMENT
OF DEFENSE OFFICE OF INSPECTOR GENERAL.
THEN I WAS REQUESTED TO JOIN THE UNITED STATES MARINE CORPS
AND TO FILE THIS REPORT, READ IT, LOOK AT THE FACTS AND WITH
AN OPEN MIND PARTNER WITH OTHER LEADERS IN THIS CITY WHO ARE
BEING BRIEFED AS OF THIS MORNING BY SENIOR MILITARY
OFFICERS. >> BEFORE YOU LOOK AT ANYONE
ELSE AT THE STATE LEVEL OR FEDERAL GOVERNMENT, YOU HAVE TO
LOOK HERE LOCALLY AND THAT'S WHAT I AM ASKING EACH OF YOU TO
DO. THERE ARE SOME PEOPLE ON THIS
REPORT THAT ARE NAMED AS SUSPECTS.
THERE ARE OTHERS THAT ARE NOT NAMED BECAUSE THOSE ARE STILL
RECORDS. SO I REQUEST TO HAVE SOMEONE
TAKE OVER THIS REPORT FOR GOOD EVENING BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
>> MY NAME IS TOMMY LAGANA AND AS A LIFELONG MEANIE WRITER
OOPS SORRY ABOUT THAT. >> THE REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU
. I'M HERE TODAY TO SPEAK
IN SUPPORT OF DECLARING SEPTEMBER 2025 AS MINI HERITAGE
MONTH FOR OVER A CENTURY MINI HAS PROVIDED EQUITABLE
TRANSPORTATION TO GENERATIONS OF SAN FRANCISCANS.
IT'S BECOMING A DEFINING PART OF OUR CITY'S HISTORY
AND CULTURE. AND YESTERDAY, SEPTEMBER 1ST
MARKED 108 YEARS OF MINI BUS SERVICE IN SAN FRANCISCO AS A
PIONEERING MUNICIPALLY OWNED TRANSIT SYSTEM.
MINI HAS LONG PROVIDED ACCESSIBLE VEHICLES
AND SERVICES DESIGNED TO MEET THE NEEDS OF ALL RIDERS
DEMONSTRATING AN UNWAVERING DEVOTION TO INCLUSIVE PUBLIC
SERVICE. TODAY THANKS TO THE WORK OF THE
SFM TO IN THE MARKET STREET RAILWAY MUNI'S HERITAGE IS KEPT
ALIVE THROUGH THEIR HISTORIC BUSSES, STREETCARS AND CABLE
CARS. THE BELOVED F LINE THE SAN
FRANCISCO RAILWAY MUSEUM AND THE UPCOMING MINI HERITAGE
WEEKEND FOR RESIDENTS AND VISITORS ALIKE THE CHANCE
TO EXPERIENCE THESE CHERISHED SYMBOLS OF SAN FRANCISCO'S
IDENTITY AND TRANSIT LEGACY BY RECOGNIZING SEPTEMBER 2025 AS
MEANING HERITAGE MONTH, WE HONOR THE DEDICATION OF THE MTA
IN THE MARKET STREET RAILWAY STAFF IN PRESERVING MUNI'S
HISTORY, CELEBRATING NOT ONLY THEIR WORK FOR THE ENJOYMENT OF
ALL BUT ALSO THE ROLE MUNI HAS PLAYED IN SHAPING SAN
FRANCISCO'S UNIQUE CHARACTER. I URGE THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
TO SUPPORT THIS DECLARATION AND JOIN IN CELEBRATING MORE
THAN A CENTURY OF MUNI SERVICE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME. OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> ALL RIGHT. HI MY NAME IS JULIA TOSCANO,
COORDINATOR WITH THE NORCAL TPS COALITION AND I'M SPEAKING
IN REGARDS TO THE RESOLUTION BROUGHT TO YOU TO VOTE TODAY TO
URGE CONGRESSIONAL DELEGATION TO URGE CONGRESS TO CREATE A
PERMANENT RESIDENCY PATHWAY FOR ALL TEMPORARY PROTECTED STATUS
TPS HOLDERS. >> MANY OF THESE TIPS HOLDERS
IN THIS CITY ARE WORKERS THEY WORK IN HEALTH CARE.
THEY ARE EDUCATORS. THEY WORK AT OUR AIRPORT.
THEY WORK IN THE FOOD SERVICE INDUSTRY.
THEIR JANITORS. >> THIS REVOKING THIS TEMPORARY
PROTECTED STATUS THAT PROTECTS THESE WORKERS IN SAN FRANCISCO
IS CRUEL. AND BASED OFF OF THE JULY 29TH
CASE UNCONSTITUTIONALITY THE EQUAL PROTECTIONS CLAUSE 14TH
AMENDMENT BECAUSE OF RACIAL IT'S BEING DONE SO TO CERTAIN
COUNTRIES BASED ON RACIAL ANIMUS.
>> MANY OF THESE PEOPLE ARE IN FEAR OF THEIR THEIR LIVES.
THEY ARE BUSINESS OWNERS. THEY'VE BEEN HERE MANY FOR LIKE
30 YEARS ARE STRUGGLING TO ARE IN FEAR OF LIKE WILL THEY GET
THEIR SOCIAL SECURITY THAT THEY'VE BEEN PAYING TAXES TO
SINCE THEY'VE BEEN HERE? >> WELL, WILL THEY BE SEPARATED
FROM THEIR CHILDREN WHO WERE BORN HERE OR WILL THEY BE ABLE
TO CONTINUE WORKING AND EXTENDING THEIR WORK
PERMIT, EXTENDING THEIR RENEWING THEIR DRIVER'S
LICENSE? >> WILL THEY GET DEPORTED ID BY
ICE? >> SO THANK YOU IN ADVANCE FOR
YOUR SUPPORT IN PASSING THIS RESOLUTION AND ON BEHALF OF ALL
OF EVERYBODY WHO WAS HERE AT THE RALLY, THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
GOOD AFTERNOON. I'M TAB BUCKNER AND I WOULD
LIKE TO ECHO WHAT JULIA JUST SAID ABOUT THE TPS RESOLUTION
AND REALLY TAKEN THE GRAVITY ALL OF ALL OF THIS.
AS MENTIONED EARLIER IN THIS MEETING, OUR DEMOCRACY IS UNDER
ASSAULT AND IT'S ABSOLUTELY CRITICAL THAT WE HAVE A
UNANIMOUS VOTE FROM THIS BOARD TO SHOW THAT SAN FRANCISCO HAS
A VERY, VERY STRONG VOICE IN SUPPORTING THE COMMUNITY
THAT WE SO REGULARLY ON A DAY TO DAY BASIS RELY ON.
THIS IS ONE OF A COURSE OF COMPASSION AND FAIRNESS
AND ALSO WE WOULD BE VERY SELF-DEFEATING AND NOT
SUPPORTING THIS COMMUNITY BECAUSE WE RELY ON THEM IN SO
MANY ESSENTIAL WAYS IN SO MANY DIFFERENT PROFESSIONS
THROUGHOUT THE THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY AND RIGHT HERE IN THE
CITY. SO I URGE EVERY SINGLE ONE OF
YOU TO VOTE ON THIS. >> AND HOPEFULLY OUR MAYOR WILL
ALSO BACK YOU UP AS WELL. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, TIM BUCKNER FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME YOUR NEXT SPEAKER BOSTON OPEN.
>> I DID HAVE SOMETHING I WROTE DOWN I DON'T THINK I WANT TO
SAY WHAT I WROTE OUT. >> THEY GOT THIS ONE ON TOP OF
THE TOP OF MY HEAD STUPID VISOR .
>> CONNIE J.J. LET'S START WITH HER COMING IN TO BAY BUCHANAN'S
POINT AT THE DEMOCRATIC MEETING.
MUG IN ME. >> I GOT YOUR MUG.
YOU DIDN'T HAVE TO DO WHAT YOU DID, BUT YOU DID IT.
>> BUT ANYWAY, TIME I JUST WANT TO LET HER KNOW I CAN'T WHAT
SHE DID. MA'AM, I UNDERSTAND.
>> I'M NOT ASKING YOU TO PLEASE DO NOT ADDRESS MEMBERS DIRECTLY
. ADDRESS THE BOARD IS GOING TO
GET ADDRESSED ANYWAY. >> ANYWAY, I'M HERE TO SPEAK ON
BEHALF OF BLACK SUFFERING URBAN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> WE WILL NO LONGER KEEP SITTING HERE ALLOWING CITY
OFFICIALS COMMUNITY BASED ORGANIZATIONS TO KEEP BULLYING
US BEING RACIST TOWARDS US AND HATING ON US AT THE SAME
TIME. >> MY NAME IS MUFFY SAYS YOU
ALL AWARE OUGHT TO EAGLES AND Y'ALL ALL HAD PARTIES
AND ALL THIS DURING YOUR VACATION.
I'M MUFFY AND MUFFY IS A LITTLE DIFFERENT THAN OTHER PEOPLE
SOME OF YOUR MIGHT KNOW YOU GIVE THEM I'M SAYING I RETIRE
THAT YACHT. >> JUST CUT TO SAN FRANCISCO
THE CITY JUST CUT THE THE MENTAL HEALTH BUDGET.
SEE Y'ALL THINK MENTAL HEALTH IS PEOPLE OUT THERE ON DRUGS.
I'M MENTAL HEALTH I'M A SURVIVOR OF SAN FRANCISCO
RACIST WAR ON DRUGS AND ALL THE STUFF THEY DID TO US OUT OF
THIS POINT AND WE'RE TIRED SO ONE OF THE THINGS WE'RE GOING
TO HAVE TO PROBABLY DO IS WE'RE GOING TO HAVE TO TAKE MATTERS
IN OUR OWN HANDS AS I COME BACK AND WATCH ALL OUR DOING WHITES,
ASIANS AND OTHERS YOU GET WHAT I'M SAYING BECAUSE WE'RE TIRED
AND WHEN I HAVE TO READ BOOKS LIKE RAVEN THE UNTOLD STORY OF
JIM JONES AND SEASON OF THE WITCH AND TRUMP THE CULT OF
TRUMP I'M SO SURE THERE IS A REASON WHY THIS CITY OPERATES
THE WAY IT WAS LIKE DIANNE FEINSTEIN A CO MORSI BECAUSE
YOU ALL SIT AROUND HERE LIKE STUPID VISORS AND I'M GONE.
>> THANK YOU THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER TODAY.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON. MY NAME IS AMY VILORIA.
I'M THE OUTREACH AND ORGANIZING MANAGER FOR SAN FRANCISCO
TRANSIT RIDERS. IT'S HOT OUT THERE.
IT'S SEPTEMBER AND IT'S ALSO TRANSIT MONTH.
THANK YOU TO SUPERVISOR MELGAR FOR INTRODUCING THE RESOLUTION
RECOGNIZING SEPTEMBER AS TRANSIT MONTH AND REAFFIRMING
THE SUPPORT FOR PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION.
PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION IS THE MOST EFFICIENT AND AFFORDABLE
WAY FOR SAN FRANCISCANS TO GET AROUND.
IT IS A PUBLIC GOOD THAT WE THE PEOPLE OWN AND IT ONLY BENEFITS
ONLY TRANSIT RIDERS BUT S.F. AS A WHOLE.
FROM REDUCE CONGESTIONS INCREASED TRAFFIC SAFETY,
INCREASED ECONOMIC BENEFITS AND OF COURSE ITS ENVIRONMENTAL
BENEFITS. LET'S CELEBRATE TRANSIT MONTH
BY PROMOTING AND USING TRANSIT. LET'S CONTINUE TO ADVOCATE
AND FIGHT FOR IT. AND FINALLY LET'S CELEBRATE BY
HAVING LOTS OF FUN. YES, THE YEAR'S THEME IS
ADVENTURES STARTS ON TRANSIT. THERE'S PLENTY OF ADVENTURES TO
BE HAD IN THE BAY AND YOU CAN START BY TAKING A TRANSIT.
WE LOOK FORWARD TO SEEING THE MEMBERS OF THE BOARD AND OUR
MAYOR FOR JOINING THE RIDE ALONG THIS THURSDAY AND ALSO
JOINING US IN FRONT OF CITY HALL FOR THE KICKOFF RALLY.
WE ALSO LOOK FORWARD FOR WHAT I PRESUME WILL BE A UNANIMOUS
VOTE FOR THIS RESOLUTION. THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR YOUR
TIME. THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR YOUR
CONTINUED SUPPORT OF PUBLIC TRANSIT AND WE LOOK FORWARD TO
YOUR LEADERSHIP IN KEEPING OUR PUBLIC TRANSIT ALIVE SO WE CAN
THRIVE. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS BEFORE BEFORE WE GO TO THE NEXT
SPEAKER. >> SIR, JUST PAUSE ONE MOMENT.
ARE THERE ANY OTHER MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC WHO WOULD LIKE TO
ADDRESS THE BOARD DURING GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT?
IF SO, PLEASE LINE UP ON THE RIGHT HAND SIDE YOUR RIGHT HAND
SIDE OF THE ROOM. WELCOME SIR.
>> THANK YOU, STEVE. AND GO OUT TO A SAN FRANCISCO
RESIDENT HOMEOWNER OF DISTRICT TEN AND I'M HERE TODAY TO THANK
EVERYBODY WHO WE WALKED AROUND AND LOBBIED A LITTLE BIT TO
GAIN SUPPORT OF TPS THE RESOLUTION IN FRONT OF YOU ITEM
NUMBER 15 AND I'M GOING TO SHARE SOME STORIES OF REAL LIFE
PEOPLE LIVING WITH TPS AND WHAT COULD HAPPEN IF WE DO NOT
PROTECT THESE PEOPLE. SO YESTERDAY WAS LABOR DAY.
I DECIDED RATHER THAN TO USE MY DAY OFF TO GO AND MEET WITH AN
OLD LADY WHO I SUPPORTED TO GET REHOUSED HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
SHE WAS DISPLACED BY AN OWNER MOVING EVICTION WHICH WE ALL
KNOW BECAME A VERY BIG THING HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO AND A LOT
OF OUR FOLKS WERE DISPLACED. WE THANKFULLY HAVE A PREFERENCE
IN AFFORDABLE HOUSING TO ALLOW FOR FOLKS IN HER SITUATION TO
GET REHOUSED. WE SUCCESSFULLY REHOUSE HER
WITH HELP OF MANY FOLKS. SHOUT OUT TO MOTHER AND DI
ROMERO WHO HELPED BUT MY STORY AND HER STORY IS ENDLESS.
SHE'S BEEN A TPS RECEIVER SINCE 1994.
PAID TAXES WORKED IN OUR CITY, WORKED IN HOTELS, CLEANED
HOUSES. HER KIDS WENT TO OUR S.F.
PUBLIC SCHOOLS. HER GRANDKIDS HAVE NOW
GRADUATED FROM S.F. PUBLIC SCHOOLS.
THESE ARE FAMILIES THAT ARE GOING TO BE IMPACTED
IMMEDIATELY IF THEIR GRANDMOTHER IS REMOVED AND NOW
SENT TO UNDO. SO I AM SO HAPPY TO HEAR THAT
ALL YOU ARE ARE ON BOARD WITH US AND SUPPORTING THIS STEP AS
IT IS BEYOND THE COUNTRIES RIGHT NOW THAT WE'RE TALKING
ABOUT NEPAL, EL SALVADOR AND HONDURAS.
BUT THERE ARE 17 COUNTRIES IN TOTAL THAT THIS PROTECTION
IS PROTECTING PEOPLE. AND I URGE YOU ALL TO INFORM
YOURSELVES TO HELP INFORM OUR MAYOR, TO HELP INFORM YOUR
CONSTITUENTS ABOUT HOW IMPORTANT IT IS TO NOT ONLY
STAND FOR THE PERSON NEXT TO YOU BUT TO STAND FOR THE PERSON
BEHIND YOU AND EVERYBODY IN THE ROOM.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER .
GOOD AFTERNOON. BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
AND PRESIDENT ADELMAN. MY NAME IS RICHARD STEVE
PETERSON. I LIKE TO COME TO THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS MEETINGS. THEY ARE ESSENTIALLY OUR HOUSE
OF COMMONS. I SAW THE HOUSE OF COMMONS ON
THE TV THE OTHER NIGHT AND IT SEEMED TO BE QUITE A LOT MORE
LIVELY THAN WHAT OCCURS IN. AND THIS AUGUST ARENA.
>> ANYWAY, I JUST WANT TO COMMENT THAT SAN FRANCISCO I
HOPE YOU REALIZE DODGED A BULLET AND THAT WAS REALLY
FORTUITOUS. WE AND I SPEAK ABOUT THE LAST
TWO ELECTION I NONE OF THE CANDIDATES THAT I SUPPORTED
NONE WERE ELECTED. HOWEVER COMING UP TO THE MIDDLE
AS A CONSERVATIVE OUR MAYOR BECAME AN ELECTED
MAYOR AND HE'S RUNNING HE'S RUNNING A FAIRLY DECENT SHIFT
THE WAY I SEE IT. BUT HE'S GOING TO NEED OUR
BACKING AND THE THING IS THAT ICE IS GOING TO TARGET NOT US
SO MUCH ANYMORE DUE TO THE ELECTION OF A PRIVILEGED WHITE
MALE BUT BECAUSE THE CITY OF OAKLAND STILL IS RUN BY NOT
ONLY A MAYOR WHO IS BLACK BUT A FORMER SENATOR WHO IS BLACK.
>> AND SO OAKLAND IS GOING TO NEED ALL THE HELP THAT WE CAN
GIVE IT. AND LET'S FACE IT LOOK AT THIS
AUGUST BODY. IT'S KIND OF LIKE THE VILLAGE
PEOPLE. I MEAN WE GOT SOMEBODY FROM
EVERYWHERE. ANYWAY, THAT'S ALL I GOT TO SAY
AND OH SHOUT OUT FOR MEANING HORSE.
HEY, I'M HAVING A PARTY. I'LL TALK TO YOU LATER.
BYE. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
ALL RIGHT. I GUESS THIS WILL BE OUR LAST
SPEAKER SINCE YES, IT'S GOING TO BE THE LAST ONE.
>> WELCOME, MISS. >> SINCE THE EVOLUTION OF AN
INTELLIGENCE LEADS TO THIS, THE MESSAGE IS CLEAR.
SO YOU NEED YOU HERE YOU NEED TO STOP WALKING FOR THE
PEDOPHILES THAT NOW RUN THE GOVERNMENT.
THAT'S IT. IF YOU ARE A PEDOPHILE YOURSELF
YOU CAN ONLY REPENT BECAUSE NO MATTER WHAT YOU DID WAS AN
OPERATION BECAUSE YOU ARE EXTREME DANGER.
RIGHT NOW KIDS ARE BEING NOT ONLY IT'S NOT ONLY PEDOPHILIA,
OF COURSE IT'S STRAIGHT TRAFFICKING.
>> SACRIFICE. >> DO YOU WANT ME TO BRING A
SEVEN YEAR OLD HERE IN FRONT OF YOU TO SHOW TO THE WORLD WHAT
THEY DO TO THEM? >> OKAY, SO I'M GOING TO GIVE
YOU A PERFECT WAY TO GET OUT OF IT.
>> YEAH, BECAUSE YOU ARE TRAPPED OBVIOUSLY ON BLACKMAIL.
>> THAT'S THE ADVANTAGE YOU HAVE WITH CALLING OUT THE
PEDOPHILES IS THAT IT WILL MAKE YOU EXONERATED FROM ANYTHING
ELSE WRONG THAT YOU'VE BEEN COMMITTING SINCE NOT ELECTED AS
YOU KNOW. BECAUSE BECAUSE YOU AGREED TO
FOLLOW THE AGENDA OF PEDOPHILES THE THIS IS A COVER UP AS THE
WORLD ALL OVER THE CITY ALREADY NOW IT'S SPREADING EVERYWHERE
INSTALLS STOP WORKING FOR PEDOPHILES.
>> EVERYBODY HATES NOW THE WORLD ALMOST IT'S WORKING.
>> I GUARANTEE YOU YOU HAVE DONE SO YOU SHOW IF YOU STOP
WORKING FOR PEDOPHILES YOU UNDERSTAND LEARN HOW TO YOU
GUYS OUT DON'T DO AS I SAY OTHERWISE GAME OVER FOR I WILL
SAY YES THE CALL THEM OUT IF YOU ARE NOT ONE AND YOU WILL
EXONERATE YOURSELF FOR ANYTHING WRONG INCLUDING CLIMATE
AGGRESSION, FOOD POISONING ALL OF IT UNDERSTAND IT'S YOUR
CHANCE. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
ARE THERE ANY OTHER SPEAKERS TO ADDRESS THE BOARD DURING
GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT? SEEING NONE MR. PRESIDENT.
ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED. LET'S GO TO OUR ADOPTION FOR
ADOPTION OF THAT COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA ITEMS 12
THROUGH 16 ITEMS 12 THROUGH 16 WERE INTRODUCED FOR ADOPTION
BUT WITHOUT REFERENCE TO COMMITTEE A UNANIMOUS VOTE IS
REQUIRED FOR ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION ON FIRST APPEARANCE
TODAY ALTERNATIVE V A MEMBER MAY REQUIRE A RESOLUTION ON
FIRST APPEARANCE TO GO TO COMMITTEE.
>> I DON'T SEE ANYONE IN THE QUEUE SO MADAM CLERK CAN YOU
PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS 12 THROUGH 16 SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES SUPERVISOR
RANDLEMAN HI MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR FOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO IN GUARDIAN EITHER ARE LEBANESE
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED MADAM
CLERK DO WE HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS?
I HAVE NONE TO REPORT MR. PRESIDENT, COULD YOU PLEASE
READ THE IN MEMORIAM? YESTERDAY'S MEETING WILL BE
ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUALS
ON BEHALF OF PRESIDENT MANDOLIN FOR THE LATE FATHER MARIO PAUL
FARINA ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR SAUDER FOR THE LATE MISS
CHRISTINA MOYLAN ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR WALTON FOR THE LATE
MR. SAMUEL MURRAY AND ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR AND GAUDIO FOR
THE LATE FATHER EDWARD REESE. I BELIEVE THAT BRINGS US TO THE
END OF OUR AGENDA MADAM CLERK. >> IS THERE ANY FURTHER
BUSINESS BEFORE US TODAY? THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS FOR
TODAY THAN IN THAT CASE? >> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK WE ARE
ADJOURNED